<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" media="screen" href="/~d/styles/rss2full.xsl"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" media="screen" href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~d/styles/itemcontent.css"?><rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:feedburner="http://rssnamespace.org/feedburner/ext/1.0" version="2.0">

<channel>
	<title>Nettuts+</title>
	
	<link>http://net.tutsplus.com</link>
	<description>Web Development &amp; Design Tutorials</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2009 20:54:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<generator>http://wordpress.org/?v=2.8.4</generator>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
			<image><link>http://nettuts.com</link><url>http://envato.s3.amazonaws.com/rss_images/nettuts.jpg</url><title>NETTUTS</title></image><atom10:link xmlns:atom10="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" rel="self" href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/nettuts" type="application/rss+xml" /><feedburner:emailServiceId>nettuts</feedburner:emailServiceId><feedburner:feedburnerHostname>http://feedburner.google.com</feedburner:feedburnerHostname><atom10:link xmlns:atom10="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" rel="hub" href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com" /><item>
		<title>Holiday Giveaways, Freebies and More!</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/nettuts/~3/tnaP8WGlnKw/</link>
		<comments>http://net.tutsplus.com/articles/news/holiday-giveaways-freebies-and-more/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2009 09:36:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Collis Ta'eed</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://net.tutsplus.com/?p=8112</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<img src="http://envato.s3.amazonaws.com/holidays/200.jpg">]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s hard to believe it&#8217;s almost a new decade, and with 2010 just around the corner it&#8217;s time to get celebrating the holiday season. There&#8217;s plenty happening around the <a href="http://envato.com">Envato</a> network of sites, read on to find out about it all!</p>
<p><span id="more-8112"></span></p>
<h2><a href="http://graphicriver.net/free-illustrations">27 Free Christmas Illustrations</a></h2>
<div class="tutorial_image"><a href="http://graphicriver.net/free-illustrations"><img src="http://envato.s3.amazonaws.com/holidays/1.jpg" alt="Free Christmas Illustrations" width="550" height="234" border="0" /></a></div>
<p>The best thing about the holiday season is getting presents, so we asked the very talented <a href="http://kailoon.com">Kai Loon</a> to put together a special set of completely free illustrations to give away. The set includes 27 illustrations to mix and match with everything you need to make cards and promotions. <a href="http://graphicriver.net/free-illustrations">Download the set for free, to use in personal or commercial projects.</a></p>
<h2>Seasonal Files!</h2>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img  src="http://envato.s3.amazonaws.com/holidays/2.jpg" alt="Seasonal Files" width="550" height="234" border="0" /></div>
<p>Around this time of year you often find yourself in need of some creative assets themed for Christmas, new year and the holidays! We&#8217;ve assembled some of the best seasonal files from around the Envato Marketplaces into 5 great collections:</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="http://activeden.net/collections/346362-happy-holidays-from-activeden">Top Holiday Flash Files</a></li>
<li><a href="http://audiojungle.net/collections/349346-best-christmas-holiday-music-on-audiojungle">Christmas &amp; Holiday Music</a></li>
<li><a href="http://graphicriver.net/collections/352998-holidays-at-graphicriver">Seasonal Vectors and Graphics</a></li>
<li><a href="http://videohive.net/collections/350250-happy-holidays-09">Holiday Themed Motion Graphics</a></li>
<li><a href="http://themeforest.net/collections/359589-best-holiday-email-templates">Seasonal Email Templates</a></li>
</ol>
<h2><a href="http://mac.appstorm.net/general/appstorm-news/the-7000-appstorm-christmas-giveaway/">$7000 of Giveaways over 24 Days on AppStorm</a></h2>
<div class="tutorial_image"><a href="http://mac.appstorm.net/general/appstorm-news/the-7000-appstorm-christmas-giveaway/"><img src="http://envato.s3.amazonaws.com/holidays/3.jpg" alt="AppStorm Christmas Giveaway" width="550" height="234" border="0" /></a></div>
<p>Enjoy apps? Well our two App review blogs &#8211; <a href="http://mac.appstorm.net">Mac.AppStorm</a> and <a href="http://web.appstorm.net">Web.AppStorm</a> &#8211; are running giveaways every single day for 24 days leading up to Christmas! It&#8217;s a total of 138 licenses worth over $7000 up for grabs, and David&#8217;s even thrown in a few free AppStorm holiday wallpapers! And if you enjoy AppStorm, look out for our third AppStorm site which is due to launch right after the giveaways, along with a redesign and a hub site at AppStorm.net!</p>
<h2><a href="http://themeforest.net/winter-wordpress">Winter of WordPress</a></h2>
<div class="tutorial_image"><a href="http://themeforest.net/winter-wordpress"><img src="http://envato.s3.amazonaws.com/holidays/4.jpg" alt="Winter of WordPress" width="550" height="234" border="0" /></a></div>
<p><a href="http://themeforest.net">Selling WordPress themes</a> has rapidly turned into a cottage industry allowing web designers and developers everywhere to earn a steady stream of income ranging from hundreds to many thousands of dollars a month. Because the quiet winter months are one of the best times to invest some time theming we&#8217;ve put together a little showcase site called Winter of WordPress to tell you all about the opportunities in WP theming!</p>
<h2>96 Tuts+ Giveaways + Wallpaper + Caricatures</h2>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img  src="http://envato.s3.amazonaws.com/holidays/5.jpg" alt="James White Wallpaper Preview" width="550" height="234" border="0" /></div>
<p>For 12 days starting on December 21st, <a href="http://tutsplus.com">Tuts+</a> is going to be hosting a massive set of 96 giveaways across all 8 Tuts+ sites including pillows, books, Amazon vouchers and Plus memberships. On New Year&#8217;s Day there will also be a special 2010 wallpaper by <a href="http://signalnoise.com/">James White</a> and our very own <a href="http://www.snaptin.com/">Ian Yates</a> is putting together caricatures of the entire Tuts+ team <img src='http://net.tutsplus.com/wp-includes/images/smilies/icon_smile.gif' alt=':-)' class='wp-smiley' />  </p>
<h2>Special Edition Comics Plus ThinkGeek Giveaways</h2>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img  src="http://envato.s3.amazonaws.com/holidays/6.jpg" alt="FreelanceFreedom Holiday Edition" width="550" height="234" border="0" /></div>
<p>Over on our work blogs <a href="http://freelanceswitch.com">FreelanceSwitch</a> and <a href="http://workawesome.com">WorkAwesome</a> we&#8217;re celebrating the holiday season with <a href="http://thinkgeek.com">ThinkGeek</a> and <a href="http://marketcircle.com">Marketcircle</a> giveaways along with our annual NC Winter&#8217;s <a href="http://freelanceswitch.com/category/freelance-freedom/">FreelanceFreedom</a> and <a href="http://workawesome.com/category/memorandom/">Memo:random</a> special comic strips!</p>
<h2>Happy New Year from Envato!</h2>
<p>So keep an eye out for it all happening across the Envato network throughout December! And from all of us here at Envato, have a lovely holiday season and a happy new year!</p>

<p><a href="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/PCqzdSDTOrvj6zyDE54H_Su_C7I/0/da"><img src="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/PCqzdSDTOrvj6zyDE54H_Su_C7I/0/di" border="0" ismap="true"></img></a><br/>
<a href="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/PCqzdSDTOrvj6zyDE54H_Su_C7I/1/da"><img src="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/PCqzdSDTOrvj6zyDE54H_Su_C7I/1/di" border="0" ismap="true"></img></a></p><div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=tnaP8WGlnKw:9RTe5mg_cL0:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=tnaP8WGlnKw:9RTe5mg_cL0:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=tnaP8WGlnKw:9RTe5mg_cL0:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=tnaP8WGlnKw:9RTe5mg_cL0:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=tnaP8WGlnKw:9RTe5mg_cL0:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=tnaP8WGlnKw:9RTe5mg_cL0:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=tnaP8WGlnKw:9RTe5mg_cL0:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=tnaP8WGlnKw:9RTe5mg_cL0:TzevzKxY174"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?d=TzevzKxY174" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/nettuts/~4/tnaP8WGlnKw" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://net.tutsplus.com/articles/news/holiday-giveaways-freebies-and-more/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>20</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://net.tutsplus.com/articles/news/holiday-giveaways-freebies-and-more/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>15 Most Important Considerations when Choosing a Web Development Framework</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/nettuts/~3/RREQx6hB8Io/</link>
		<comments>http://net.tutsplus.com/tutorials/other/15-most-important-considerations-when-choosing-a-web-development-framework/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2009 08:30:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Siddharth</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Other]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[framework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[web development]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[web development framework]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://net.tutsplus.com/?p=8035</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/510_webFramework/200x200.jpg" alt="How to Choose a Web Development Framework" />]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>New web development frameworks are sprouting out at a more rapid pace than anyone could keep up with. In this article, we are going to determine how to decide on a framework for creating your next, hot web application.
</p>
<p><span id="more-8035"></span></p>
<p>In this current day and age, pushing out a finished, polished application well before your competitor is key. Coding everything from scratch, excluding even the mundane things,  can be extremely time consuming and makes the developer spend time reinventing the wheel, time which would rather be spent implementing new features or tightening up the code base. This is where web development frameworks come in. They often cover all the usual aspects of an application including database access, authentication, session management and much more.</p>
<p>Today, we are going to take a look at the various aspects you should be concerned about before choosing a framework. Interested? Let&#8217;s get started right away!</p>
<h3>1. Usage Context</h3>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/510_webFramework/images/usage.jpg" alt="Tutorial Image" border="0" /></div>
<p>Before you even start looking at a frameworks, you&#8217;ll need to make a list of your requirements and whether a framework is suitable for that purpose. </p>
<h4>You are in need of a framework if:</h4>
<ul>
<li>your application is primarily based on CRUD operations</li>
<li>you need proper separation of the UI and underlying logic but don&#8217;t have the time to implement a proper system</li>
<li>you find yourself having a self made library you use in each of your applications covering user authentication, sessions and other usual operations associated with creating a web application</li>
<li>you have a boss who wants you to create a CMS for them in 2 days and you already know the framework</li>
</ul>
<h4>You DON&#8217;T need a framework if:</h4>
<ul>
<li>you want a pretty URL system alone</li>
<li>you want only a specific part of the framework like its ORM</li>
<li>you are on a tight timeline and you need to learn the framework from scratch</li>
<li>you were told frameworks cure cancer</li>
</ul>
<h3>2. License</h3>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/510_webFramework/images/license.png" alt="Tutorial Image" border="0" /></div>
<p>Before you start developing with a framework, see what kind of license the framework is distributed under. While most licenses are pretty liberal to work with and lets you create commercial applications, some of them are not so generous. The last thing you&#8217;d want is to create an entire application only to find out that the license doesn&#8217;t allow you to distribute it commercially. Better do your research before than suffering after.</p>
<p>Do note that this isn&#8217;t limited to the framework alone. The plugin or extension you made use of for the extra functionality may have a hidden clause. Check it&#8217;s license too!</p>
<h3>3. Software Pattern</h3>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/510_webFramework/images/mvc.png" alt="Tutorial Image" border="0" /><br />From the Symfony project</div>
<p>Almost every framework out there exclusively uses the MVC pattern. MVC, which stands for Model-View-Controller, helps you keep your data: the model, the  logic: the controller and the user interface: the view, separate from each other. This in turn lets you write better, tighter code which ultimately results in better applications. </p>
<p>Just because almost everyone uses MVC doesn&#8217;t mean that is everything you need to know though. There are a couple of variants including MVP: Model-View-Presenter, MVA: Model-View-Adapter and AVC: Application-View-Controller.</p>
<h3>4. Hosting Requirements</h3>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/510_webFramework/images/host.jpg" alt="Tutorial Image" border="0" /></div>
<p>As web developers, we may be inclined to building applications on cutting edge platforms but often the need and budget of the client comes first. Often it may be out of the budget to get a dedicated host to place our applications on and we&#8217;ll have to settle with shared hosting with normal modules and settings.</p>
<p>Frameworks which play nice with shared hosting include:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.codeigniter.com">CodeIgniter</a></li>
<li><a href="http://cakephp.org/">CakePHP</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.kohanaphp.com/">Kohana</a></li>
<li><a href="http://framework.zend.com/">Zend Framework</a></li>
<li>Most other PHP frameworks</li>
</ul>
<p>Frameworks which require relatively non-traditional setups:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://rubyonrails.org/">Ruby on Rails</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.djangoproject.com/">Django</a></li>
<li><a href="http://pylonshq.com/">Pylons</a></li>
<li>Most non-PHP frameworks</li>
</ul>
<p>In all honesty though, you can still run frameworks like Django off an off the shelf shared host. It&#8217;ll just require that the server has the necessary module installed. You may be able to run it off CGI but it&#8217;ll be a lot slower than running it natively.</p>
<h3>5. Ease of Installation</h3>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/510_webFramework/images/install.jpg" alt="Tutorial Image" border="0" /></div>
<p>Ease of installation plays a very important role whilst choosing a framework. A framework, however feature laden or quick it may be, can pose quite a problem if one has to run through a number of steps just to get it installed and working. </p>
<p>This will also pose a big problem once the application is ready, tested and needs to be deployed to the production server. A framework with ease of installation and just as easy deployment gets brownie points here.</p>
<p>For a lot of the frameworks, set up is as simple as setting the right values in the configuration file whilst for others it may be a very time consuming, elaborate affair. Choose a framework which lets you get up and running as rapidly as possible.</p>
<h3>6. Learning Curve</h3>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/510_webFramework/images/learningcurve.jpg" alt="Tutorial Image" border="0" /></div>
<p>Every framework has its own tiny universe: naming conventions, directory structure and what nots. Some frameworks are rather flexible when it comes to these while others are very, very strict throwing up errors at the tiniest of mistakes. Some frameworks follow general conventions while implementing a feature while others may strike out and do its own thing. While choosing a framework, remember to choose one that has the smallest possible learning curve. </p>
<p>If you don&#8217;t know the language the framework is written in, make a note of including the language itself to the learning curve. I&#8217;ve seen a number of developers jumping to Django from CakePHP and struggling since they need to learn both Python and Django at the same time. If you need to learn both the framework and the language it was written in, pace yourself!</p>
<h3>7. Core Library</h3>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/510_webFramework/images/core.png" alt="Tutorial Image" border="0" /></div>
<p>Let&#8217;s face it; it is for the core library that most people adopt a framework. The library must be in such as that it frees you from writing repetitive code but still provides a way for you to tinker with it if you need more control or features. </p>
<p>Most frameworks offer libraries which cover almost all of the following list:</p>
<ul>
<li>AJAX</li>
<li>Authentication</li>
<li>Authorization</li>
<li>Caching</li>
<li>Data Sanitization</li>
<li>Data Validation</li>
<li>Templating</li>
<li>URL mapping or rewriting</li>
</ul>
<p>Of course, not every one needs a framework brimming with features. A lot of people prefer frameworks to handle the bare minimum whilst letting the developer handle the rest. In these cases, you&#8217;ll need to make sure the framework in question has only the features you need.</p>
<p>A current trend among frameworks is that they are created as a library of libraries. In other words, it lets you swap out parts of the library with another part of your choice. An excellent example of this would be Pylons. It lets you switch out almost all of its parts starting from the ORM right down to its templating language. People like these loosely coupled frameworks just as much as the frameworks which are tightly couple with respect to its core components.</p>
<h3>8. DB Abstraction and ORM</h3>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/510_webFramework/images/orm.jpg" alt="Tutorial Image" border="0" /></div>
<p>Almost every application has to access a database to either read data off or edit its contents. Either way, you&#8217;ll be doing this along the length of the application and with this in mind, most frameworks lets you use an database access class you can make a use of. So while choosing an application, choose one which lets your application become database agnostic. You&#8217;ll never have to care about the database part incase you need to switch out databases if your framework takes care of that.</p>
<p>The second part you&#8217;ll need to think about is the framework&#8217;s ORM capabilities. Without getting technical, ORM or Object Relational Mapping lets you express data as an object and see how it relates to other objects. Imagine an object database you can pull information from, if you will. </p>
<p>Frameworks which have ORM capabilities include CakePHP, Django and Ruby. With frameworks like Pylons, you can use your ORM of choice.</p>
<h3>9. Included JS Library</h3>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/510_webFramework/images/js.jpg" alt="Tutorial Image" border="0" /></div>
<p>Another point of contention is the bundled JavaScript library. While most libraries let you swap out the library with ease, the AJAX methods inside the framework are mostly still aimed towards a specific JS library. This implicitly means that you&#8217;ll have to manually write the functionality yourself. On the other hand are frameworks with library agnostic methods which let you swap out the JavaScript library with little to no hassle.</p>
<p>Just as a reference, both CakePHP and Ruby on Rails ship with Prototype and Scriptaculous as standard. </p>
<h3>10. Unit Testing</h3>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/510_webFramework/images/unittest.png" alt="Tutorial Image" border="0" /></div>
<p>I am one of those developers who swear by unit testing. Wikipedia defines unit testing as:</p>
<p><em>Unit testing is a software verification and validation method in which a programmer tests if individual units of source code are fit for use. A unit is the smallest testable part of an application.</em></p>
<p>Frameworks which lets me write unit tests are a definite plus in this case. A lot of frameworks including Code Igniter, CakePHP and Zend lets you create custom tests in addition to the core tests to check the critical parts of your application.</p>
<h3>11. Scaling</h3>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/510_webFramework/images/scaling.jpg" alt="Tutorial Image" border="0" /></div>
<p>The average web developer doesn&#8217;t have to worry about the scalability of a framework. As often is the case,  I/O and network latency are often the issue rather than a framework&#8217;s scalability. Even Twitter&#8217;s mythical scalability problem wasn&#8217;t the fault of the framework in question.</p>
<p>If someone asks you to layoff a framework pointing out <em>scaling problems,</em> disregard them. The framework is rarely the reason of the scaling issue. Sure, you could optimize the code a little bit but often the brunt of the scaling issue lies elsewhere.</p>
<h3>12. Documentation</h3>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/510_webFramework/images/docs.jpg" alt="Tutorial Image" border="0" /></div>
<p>A framework&#8217;s documentation is often key to its success. Well explained, detailed documentation draws in the power users and evangelists who then bring in more people. With shoddy, confusing documentation  people are going to just walk off confused and annoyed. </p>
<p>Look for a framework which has thorough documentation with plenty of examples, snippets, sample code, articles and tutorials. Screencasts like Jeffrey&#8217;s are a special plus since it&#8217;ll let you zip right along.</p>
<h3>13. The Community</h3>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/510_webFramework/images/community.jpg" alt="Tutorial Image" border="0" /></div>
<p>Inevitably, even with proper documentation, you are going to run into errors to rectify which, you are going to have to ask the community behind the framework for help. I&#8217;ve personally interacted with communities which vitriolically attacked programmers new to the framework and sneered at them while on the other extreme I&#8217;ve seen communities cheerfully welcomes newbies and teach them the tricks of the trade. I think there is no need to say which framework I ended up choosing and started working permanently on.</p>
<p>As often is the case, the communities behind a framework make or break the framework. Too snobby and you&#8217;ll resent the framework instead of the people. Well mannered and you&#8217;ll gravitate towards the framework. Choose a framework which has a friendly community which helps developers new to the platform.</p>
<h3>14. Bug Fixes/ Updates</h3>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/510_webFramework/images/bug.jpg" alt="Tutorial Image" border="0" /></div>
<p>One of the reasons web developers shy away from just creating their own frameworks is the fact that they alone are in charge of fixing the bugs and updates. With a big framework, you literally have thousands of programmers sifting through the code and putting it through its paces on a daily basis. Bugs, if and when they are found, are squashed as soon as possible after they are found. </p>
<p>Choose a framework which isn&#8217;t stagnant. You don&#8217;t want a hacker to tell you that a security vulnerability exists in the framework through a page he hacked on your site. You&#8217;d rather hear that from the framework developers, hopefully with a link to a patch to the issue. Choose a framework which is updated often, is open about the bugs it finds and more importantly fixes the bugs people come across as soon as possible.</p>
<h3>15. Ease of Creating an Extension and Availability</h3>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/510_webFramework/images/plugin.png" alt="Tutorial Image" border="0" /></div>
<p>While a framework covers all of the important bases of an application, chances are, you&#8217;ll still have to write a bunch of code. Make it generic enough and you can re-purpose it into a component suitable for reuse in your other applications or even better release it to the general public so they make use of it in their applications.. </p>
<p>Choose a framework which lets you extend the framework easily and with minimal fuss. With CakePHP for example, extending a controller is taken care of by <em>components</em> and views by <em>helpers</em>. In either case, creating an extension is as simple as defining a new class which inherits from a parent base class.</p>
<p>While choosing a framework, also keep in mind the availability of plugins. Often you won&#8217;t have the time to create a custom extension from scratch. Having a huge pool of extensions to choose from greatly alleviates this issue. Choose not by the number of extensions but by the quality of the extensions.</p>
<h3>Conclusion</h3>
<p>And we are done! We looked at all the aspects you should consider before choosing a web development framework. We looked at everything from mapping out whether it&#8217;d suit our purposes to bug fixes and updates. Hopefully, this has been useful to you and you found it interesting.</p>
<p>Questions? Nice things to say? Criticisms? Hit the comments section and leave me a comment. Happy coding!</p>
<ul class="webroundup">
<li>Follow us on <a href="http://www.twitter.com/nettuts">Twitter</a>, or subscribe to the <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/nettuts" title="Nettuts+ RSS Feed">Nettuts+ RSS Feed</a> for the best web development tutorials on the web.</li>
</ul>
<p>
<script type="text/javascript"><!--digg_url = "post permalink (not digg url)"; // -->
</script><br />
<script src="http://digg.com/tools/diggthis.js" type="text/javascript"></script></p>

<p><a href="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/Oe0bKnnh-l5RkbC2DoHH3gFWQIM/0/da"><img src="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/Oe0bKnnh-l5RkbC2DoHH3gFWQIM/0/di" border="0" ismap="true"></img></a><br/>
<a href="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/Oe0bKnnh-l5RkbC2DoHH3gFWQIM/1/da"><img src="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/Oe0bKnnh-l5RkbC2DoHH3gFWQIM/1/di" border="0" ismap="true"></img></a></p><div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=RREQx6hB8Io:OaZVmEQ2SCg:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=RREQx6hB8Io:OaZVmEQ2SCg:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=RREQx6hB8Io:OaZVmEQ2SCg:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=RREQx6hB8Io:OaZVmEQ2SCg:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=RREQx6hB8Io:OaZVmEQ2SCg:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=RREQx6hB8Io:OaZVmEQ2SCg:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=RREQx6hB8Io:OaZVmEQ2SCg:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=RREQx6hB8Io:OaZVmEQ2SCg:TzevzKxY174"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?d=TzevzKxY174" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/nettuts/~4/RREQx6hB8Io" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://net.tutsplus.com/tutorials/other/15-most-important-considerations-when-choosing-a-web-development-framework/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>18</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://net.tutsplus.com/tutorials/other/15-most-important-considerations-when-choosing-a-web-development-framework/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>WordPress 2.7 Cookbook + Free E-Books!</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/nettuts/~3/peYYqkjd1OY/</link>
		<comments>http://net.tutsplus.com/freebies/wordpress-2-7-cookbook-free-e-books/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2009 18:50:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jeffrey Way</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Freebies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[book]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Freebie]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[review]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://net.tutsplus.com/?p=8077</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/514_wpCookbook/200x200.jpg" alt="WordPress 2.7 Cookbook" />]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<a href="http://www.packtpub.com/">Packt Publishing</a> recently sent me a review copy of &#8220;<a href="http://www.packtpub.com/wordpress-2-7-cookbook">WordPress 2.7 Cookbook.</a>&#8221; I&#8217;m a huge fan of the cookbook line; they&#8217;re similar to a huge string of quick tips. So if you don&#8217;t have time to read for an hour straight, you can always pick up a web dev cookbook and learn a few neat techniques within minutes.
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.packtpub.com/wordpress-2-7-cookbook">WordPress 2.7 Cookbook</a> is no different, and though it&#8217;s more of a quick reference book, rather than one that you would traditionally read front-to-back, I still found myself devouring the pages within a day or so.  </p>
<p><span id="more-8077"></span></p>
<div class="tutorial_image">
<a href="http://www.packtpub.com/wordpress-2-7-cookbook"><br />
   <img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/514_wpCookbook/book.jpg" alt="WordPress Cookbook" /><br />
</a>
</div>
<blockquote>
<p>&#8220;With this cookbook, you will learn many WordPress secrets and techniques, with step-by-step, useful recipes dedicated to achieving a particular goal or solve a particular problem. You&#8217;ll learn the secret of expensive premium themes, how to optimize your blog for SEO and online profits, and how to supercharge WordPress with killer functions used by the most popular blogs over the Internet.&#8221;
</p></blockquote>
<h3>Useful Tips I Picked Up</h3>
<ul>
<li>Displaying a custom login form in your blog&#8217;s sidebar </li>
<li>Using the CSS sliding doors technique within WordPress</li>
<li>Creating an iPhone friendly version of your blog. </li>
<li>Save time by using Worpress <strong>shortcodes</strong> </li>
<li>Testing your blog&#8217;s security </li>
</ul>
<p>
Ultimately, books like this one deliver exactly what you&#8217;d expect. In need of front-to-back WordPress reference? This won&#8217;t do. However, if you think you&#8217;d enjoy reading over a 100 useful tips and &#8220;recipes,&#8221; I&#8217;d pick it up!
</p>
<h3>Free E-Books </h3>
<p>
It&#8217;s become a tradition to raffle off a handful of books every week on Nettuts+. To enter for a chance to win the &#8220;<a href="http://www.packtpub.com/wordpress-2-7-cookbook">WordPress 2.7 Cookbook</a>&#8221; ebook from <a href="http://www.packtpub.com/">Packt</a>, simply leave a comment with a link to your favorite web development book ever. In twenty-four hours, I&#8217;ll filter through the comments, and will email a handful of winners! Be sure to leave some way to get in touch with you; an email address, or a link to your website should suffice.
</p>
<ul class="webroundup">
<li>Follow us on <a href="http://www.twitter.com/nettuts">Twitter</a>, or subscribe to the <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/nettuts" title="Nettuts+ RSS Feed">Nettuts+ RSS Feed</a> for the best web development tutorials on the web.</li>
</ul>
<p>
<script type="text/javascript"><!--digg_url = "post permalink (not digg url)"; // -->
</script><br />
<script src="http://digg.com/tools/diggthis.js" type="text/javascript"></script></p>

<p><a href="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/1omyMNfyTFi43Ug3uqfevkSX5t8/0/da"><img src="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/1omyMNfyTFi43Ug3uqfevkSX5t8/0/di" border="0" ismap="true"></img></a><br/>
<a href="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/1omyMNfyTFi43Ug3uqfevkSX5t8/1/da"><img src="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/1omyMNfyTFi43Ug3uqfevkSX5t8/1/di" border="0" ismap="true"></img></a></p><div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=peYYqkjd1OY:XY59y_nh1ME:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=peYYqkjd1OY:XY59y_nh1ME:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=peYYqkjd1OY:XY59y_nh1ME:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=peYYqkjd1OY:XY59y_nh1ME:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=peYYqkjd1OY:XY59y_nh1ME:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=peYYqkjd1OY:XY59y_nh1ME:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=peYYqkjd1OY:XY59y_nh1ME:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=peYYqkjd1OY:XY59y_nh1ME:TzevzKxY174"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?d=TzevzKxY174" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/nettuts/~4/peYYqkjd1OY" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://net.tutsplus.com/freebies/wordpress-2-7-cookbook-free-e-books/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>239</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://net.tutsplus.com/freebies/wordpress-2-7-cookbook-free-e-books/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>JavaScript from Null: Video Series</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/nettuts/~3/T0jTMTuCmL0/</link>
		<comments>http://net.tutsplus.com/tutorials/javascript-ajax/javascript-from-null-video-series/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2009 21:34:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jeffrey Way</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[JavaScript & AJAX]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Screencasts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ecma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[from scratch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[JavaScript]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jQuery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[js]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MooTools]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[screencast]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[series]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[video tutorial]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Videos]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://net.tutsplus.com/?p=8066</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/513_jsFromNull/javascript-from-null.jpg" alt="JavaScript From Null: Video Series" />]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
Thanks to the wide adoption of libraries like jQuery and Mootools, JavaScript&#8217;s popularity has skyrocketed in the last few years. However, in the process, an interesting thing occurred: many newer developers are learning these libraries without taking the time to actually learn about raw JavaScript techniques. What percentage of jQuery users don&#8217;t know how to fade out an element with only raw JS? My guess is that it&#8217;s much higher than many would think.
</p>
<p>If you want to truly understand the library you&#8217;re working with, and improve your skill-set, it&#8217;s vital that you learn the fundamentals of raw JavaScript. </p>
<p>This screencast series focuses exclusively on JavaScript, and will take you from your first &#8220;Hello, World&#8221; alert up to more advanced topics.<br />
<span id="more-8066"></span></p>
<div class="tutorial_image">
<a href="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/513_jsFromNull/chapter1.zip"><img src="http://nettuts.com/wp-content/themes/nettuts/site_images/button_src_nm.jpg"></a>
</div>
<h3>Chapter 1: Hello, World </h3>
<div class="tutorial_image">
<embed src="http://blip.tv/play/gcMVgbSVLwA%2Em4v" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" width="600" height="450" allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true"></embed>
</div>
<ul class="webroundup">
<li>Follow us on <a href="http://www.twitter.com/nettuts">Twitter</a>, or subscribe to the <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/nettuts" title="Nettuts+ RSS Feed">Nettuts+ RSS Feed</a> for the best web development tutorials on the web.</li>
</ul>
<p>
<script type="text/javascript"><!--digg_url = "post permalink (not digg url)"; // -->
</script><br />
<script src="http://digg.com/tools/diggthis.js" type="text/javascript"></script></p>

<p><a href="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/1_bZ8AHde24S4ZdlK6QIBTK1c8Q/0/da"><img src="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/1_bZ8AHde24S4ZdlK6QIBTK1c8Q/0/di" border="0" ismap="true"></img></a><br/>
<a href="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/1_bZ8AHde24S4ZdlK6QIBTK1c8Q/1/da"><img src="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/1_bZ8AHde24S4ZdlK6QIBTK1c8Q/1/di" border="0" ismap="true"></img></a></p><div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=T0jTMTuCmL0:Sx7tw8H5qoA:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=T0jTMTuCmL0:Sx7tw8H5qoA:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=T0jTMTuCmL0:Sx7tw8H5qoA:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=T0jTMTuCmL0:Sx7tw8H5qoA:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=T0jTMTuCmL0:Sx7tw8H5qoA:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=T0jTMTuCmL0:Sx7tw8H5qoA:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=T0jTMTuCmL0:Sx7tw8H5qoA:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=T0jTMTuCmL0:Sx7tw8H5qoA:TzevzKxY174"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?d=TzevzKxY174" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/nettuts/~4/T0jTMTuCmL0" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://net.tutsplus.com/tutorials/javascript-ajax/javascript-from-null-video-series/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>75</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://net.tutsplus.com/tutorials/javascript-ajax/javascript-from-null-video-series/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Use Sprites to Create an Awesomeness-Filled Navigation Menu</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/nettuts/~3/N8jj0wlTD6s/</link>
		<comments>http://net.tutsplus.com/tutorials/html-css-techniques/use-sprites-to-create-an-awesomeness-filled-navigation-menu/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2009 19:41:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Abhin Sharma</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[HTML & CSS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[JavaScript & AJAX]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CSS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jQuery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[menu]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[navigation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[navigation menu]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sprites]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://net.tutsplus.com/?p=8057</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/demo/images/200x200.jpg" alt="Creating an Awesome Menu using CSS Sprites and jQuery" width="200" height="200"/>]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>CSS sprites can dramatically increase a website&#8217;s performance, and with jQuery, we can implement awesome transition effects easily. Let&#8217;s get started.</p>
<p><span id="more-8057"></span></p>
<div class="tutorial_image">
<a href="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/demo/demo.zip"><img src="http://nettuts.com/wp-content/themes/nettuts/site_images/button_src_nm.jpg"></a><br />
<a href="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/demo/index.html"><img src="http://nettuts.com/wp-content/themes/nettuts/site_images/button_demo_nm.jpg"></a>
</div>
<h3>Tutorial Details</h3>
<ul>
<li><b>Requirements</b>:
<ul>
<li>Basic Knowledge of jQuery</li>
<li>Basic Knowledge of Photoshop</li>
<li>Basic Knowledge of CSS</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><b>Difficulty: Intermediate</b> </li>
<li><b>Estimated Completion Time: 40 mins</b> </li>
</ul>
<h3>What is a CSS Sprite?</h3>
<p>Sprites date back to the early days of video games, where they were used as optimization technique for displaying 2D graphics.  A CSS sprite is a technique that involves grouping images to form a single master image, and then selectively displaying only the required sections using CSS attributes (width, height, background-position etc).</p>
<p>In this tutorial we&#8217;ll create a navigation menu inspired by <a href="http://dragoninteractive.com/">Dragon Interactive</a>. They have an excellent design concept, with a perfect use of highlights and colors.</p>
<h3>Step 1</h3>
<p>Begin by creating a new Photoshop document, which is 800px wide by 500px high. </p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img1.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<h3>Step 2</h3>
<p>Next, we&#8217;ll create a horizontal ruler at the 70px mark by going to view -> new guide; this will be our menu height. </p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img2.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<h3>Step 3</h3>
<p>Now we are going to create a folder menu, and inside it, a sub folder called &#8220;Menu Text.&#8221; </p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img3.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<h3>Step 4</h3>
<p>Select the text tool(shortcut: t) and set the following properties in the character toolbox.</p>
<ul>
<li>Font: Franklin Gothic Medium Cond</li>
<li>Font Size: 15pt</li>
<li>Color: Black</li>
</ul>
<p>Other fonts can be used as well but this font family is best suited for embedded text effect which we will give later. If you don&#8217;t have this font you can get it from <a href="http://www.ascenderfonts.com/info/franklin-gothic-font.aspx">Website</a>.
</p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img4.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<h3>Step 5</h3>
<p>Create another horizontal ruler at 40px, this will help to keep our menu text horizontally aligned.</p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img5.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<h3>Step 6</h3>
<p>Now select the menu text folder, and type the menu words HOME, SERVICES, PORTFOLIO, ABOUT, and CONTACT, keeping equal spaces between each. It should now look like the image below.</p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img6.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<h3>Step 7</h3>
<p>Now create another folder below the menu text folder, and name it &#8220;Menu Background.&#8221;</p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img7.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<h3>Step 8</h3>
<p>Let&#8217;s next create a new layer inside the Menu Background folder, and then using a rectangular marquee tool, create a selection of 100px wide and 70px high. </p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img8.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<h3>Step 9</h3>
<p>Select the gradient tool (shortcut : g), and set the gradient colors from #555555 to #adadae . </p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img9.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<h3>Step 10</h3>
<p>Now draw a gradient starting from the bottom of the selection to the top of the selection; then give it a stroke with the following properties: </p>
<ul>
<li>Stroke Size : 1px</li>
<li>Position : outside</li>
<li>Color : Black</li>
</ul>
<p>
The stroke was added to provide depth to our menu divisions.
</p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img10.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<p></p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img10_1.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<h3>Step 11</h3>
<p>Now In order to achieve the highly polished ends, and to create the proper effect when the mouse hover occurs, we will give it an adjacent highlight. </p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img11.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<h3>Step 12</h3>
<p>Go to select > modify > contract and enter 1px. </p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img12.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<h3>Step 13</h3>
<p>Select the burn tool and set the following properties:</p>
<ul>
<li>Brush Size : around 200px</li>
<li>Brush Hardness : 0%</li>
<li>Range : Shadows</li>
<li>Exposure :30%</li>
</ul>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img13.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<h3>Step 14</h3>
<p>Now we will move the menu division right 1px, using the move tool(shortcut: v) in order to show the left side of the stroke, which was invisible due to its position. </p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img14.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<h3>Step 15</h3>
<p>Create copies of the above layer and adjust them with respect to the menu text. </p>
<h4>Two things that Must be Noted </h4>
<ul>
<li>Transform (ctrl + t) and increase the size of the layer underneath SERVICES and PORTFOLIO, since they are wider than the other words. Change the length from 100px to 110px.</li>
<li>The stroke of the adjacent layers must overlap each other.</li>
</ul>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img15.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img15_1.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img15_2.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<p>This is what the menu looks like when we adjust the positioning of the layers and menu text accordingly.  </p>
<h3>Step 16</h3>
<p>In order to embed the typographic effect, we add the &#8220;Drop Shadow&#8221; effect with the following settings to our text:</p>
<ul>
<li>Color: #b7b6b6</li>
<li>Opacity: 40%</li>
<li>Distance: 1px</li>
<li>Spread: 100%</li>
<li>Size: 0px</li>
</ul>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img16.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<h3>Step 17</h3>
<p>Now, its time to create what the menu looks like during the mouse hover state. Create a copy of the &#8220;Menu Background&#8221; folder, and rename it to &#8220;Menu Hover.&#8221; Then, using the move tool, move the folder 70px down so that the newly created menu&#8217;s top part touches the horizontal guide.</p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img17.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img17_1.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<p>The reason we have created the copy of the menu folder, is because we&#8217;re interested in the positioning of the menu text. If we had created it manually, then we would have to worry about the exact alignment of the menu&#8217;s text, which would be much more tedious. </p>
<h3>Step 18</h3>
<p>Now, we will select the background layer of the service menu from the &#8220;Menu Hover&#8221; folder, and give it a nice elegant effect upon the hover state. To do this, first create a selection by pressing ctrl and click on the layer; then press delete, which will delete the current shade. Next&#8230; </p>
<ul>
<li>Color &#8211; #9de0ff at 0% Location</li>
<li>Color &#8211; #0072ff at 50% Location</li>
<li>Color &#8211; #005ead at 100% Location</li>
</ul>
<p>
Select radial gradient, and draw a line from the bottom of the selection to 30px above the top of the selection.
</p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img18.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<h3>Step 19</h3>
<p>Our work is not done quite yet. To give it a smooth touch, we need to polish it a bit more. To create a more revealing menu division, we&#8217;ll make the edges darker. To achieve this, we need to add the following effects:</p>
<ul>
<li>Select the burn tool, with a brush size of 200px, range &#8211; highlight and exposure to 50%, brush it along the edges of the division.
</li>
<li>To make the edges even darker, we add an inner shadow effect:
<ul>
<li>Blend Mode : Hard light</li>
<li>Opacity : 70%</li>
<li>Distance: 0px</li>
<li>Choke: 0%</li>
<li>Size: 10px</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img19.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img19_1.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<h3>Step 20</h3>
<p>Apply a similar effect for the portfolio and about menus. For the contact menu, change the gradient colors to: </p>
<ul>
<li>Color &#8211; #ff9dbd at 0% Location</li>
<li>Color &#8211; #ff0084 at 50% Location</li>
<li>Color &#8211; #a00337 at 100% Location</li>
</ul>
<p>This what our menu looks like now:</p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img20.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<h3>Step 21</h3>
<p>The home menu division needs to be given special treatment; select the layer by pressing ctrl and clicking on the layer. Press delete to remove the current shade, and select the gradient tool with the following colors: </p>
<ul>
<li>Color &#8211; #fff5c0 at 0% Location</li>
<li>Color &#8211; #fae15d at 50% Location</li>
<li>Color &#8211; #eac500 at 100% Location</li>
</ul>
<p>
This time, select linear gradient, and draw a gradient from the top of the selection to the bottom of the selection.
</p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img21.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<h3>Step 22</h3>
<p>Select the burn tool, keeping the rest of the properties the same except for the range, set it to midtones, and apply brush strokes around the edges except for the top. </p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img22.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<h3>Step 23</h3>
<p>Now to create the glassy effect: select the pen tool, make sure that &#8220;shape fill&#8221; is selected, and draw the shape like the one in the image, and set its blend mode to soft light with an opacity of about 40%.</p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img23.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img23_1.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<h3>Step 24</h3>
<p>Two more things before we&#8217;re finished with the Photoshop part.</p>
<ul>
<li>First, the text effect within the &#8220;Menu Hover&#8221; folder is not looking elegant enough; so we change the color of the drop shadow property.
<ul>
<li> Home Menu
<ul>
<li>Color : #fff368 </li>
<li>Opacity : 80%</li>
<li>Also add gradient-overlay : #854406 to b75a03</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
Services, Portfolio and About Menus</p>
<ul>
<li>Color: #78bbff</li>
<li>Opacity : 70%</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li> Contact Menu
<ul>
<li>Color : #f78bb6 </li>
<li>opacity : 80%</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Second is the last division in Menu folder does not have an adjacent highlight to the right; so we&#8217;ll clip a small portion of the background layer, and align it next to the contact background layer. Then, we crop the image and save.</li>
</ul>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img24.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<p></p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img24_1.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<p>Finally our sprite image looks so:</p>
<h3>Step 25</h3>
<p>Now comes the coding section, which is quite easy. Create an html file, and add the following code: </p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
&lt;html>
&lt;head>
&lt;link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="style.css" />
&lt;script type="text/javascript" src="jquery.js">&lt;/script>
&lt;script type="text/javascript" src="jquery.easing.1.3.js">&lt;/script>
&lt;script type="text/javascript" src="sprite.js">&lt;/script>
&lt;title>Awesome Menu&lt;/title>
&lt;/head>

&lt;body>
&lt;div id="nav">
&lt;ul id="navigation">
	&lt;li >&lt;a class="home" href="#">&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
	&lt;li >&lt;a class="services" href="#">&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
	&lt;li >&lt;a class="portfolio" href="#">&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
	&lt;li >&lt;a class="about" href="#">&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
    &lt;li >&lt;a class="contact" href="#">&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/body>
&lt;/html>
</pre>
<p>Here we have created a simple html file, which consists of an unordered list &#8211; our navigation bar. Before moving forward, let&#8217;s take a look at a couple of files we&#8217;ll now be importing:</p>
<ul>
<li>style.css is the external CSS file in which we will be styling our navigation list. </li>
<li>We&#8217;ve imported jQuery for the animation on hover.</li>
<li>The jQuery easing plugin is also used, which we&#8217;ll review later.</li>
<li>It&#8217;s good practice to create an external js file for our work, so we also do that in &#8220;sprite.js.&#8221;</li>
</ul>
<h3>Step 26</h3>
<p>Create an external .js file, called sprite.js, and paste in the following code.</p>
<pre name="code" class="js">
$(function(){

		   $('#navigation li a').append('<span class="hover"></span>');
           // span whose opacity will animate when mouse hovers.

		   $('#navigation li a').hover(
             function() {
	         $('.hover', this).stop().animate({
			'opacity': 1
			}, 700,'easeOutSine')
        	},
            function() {
	       $('.hover', this).stop().animate({
			'opacity': 0
			}, 700, 'easeOutQuad')

	})
		   });
</pre>
<p>When the DOM is loaded, we inject a span into our anchor tag; this span will actually animate. Then, using the hover function for the anchor tag, we animate the opacity of the span. To create a smoother animation, we will use the easing equation. I am using &#8216;easeoutsine&#8217; and &#8216;easeoutquad&#8217;; feel free to try an alternative combinations, if you wish. </p>
<h3>Step 27</h3>
<p>Now comes the CSS part. Create the style.css file. Below is the initial image of what the menu looks like. For now, it&#8217;s only four dots, because we haven&#8217;t yet styled it. </p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/512_dragon/img/img25.jpg" border="0" /></div>
<h3>Step 28</h3>
<p>First, we align the list. </p>
<pre name="code" class="css">
body{
background:#000000; }

#navigation
{
margin-left:250px;
}

#navigation li
{
float:left;
}
</pre>
<p>
We&#8217;ve only moved the menu in the center a bit.
</p>
<h3>Step 29</h3>
<p>Style the anchor tag; its background will be our sprite image. </p>
<pre name="code" class="css">
#navigation li a
{
background-image:url(images/sprite.jpg);
display:block;
}
</pre>
<blockquote><p>The display style must be set to block; otherwise, nothing will be displayed. </p>
</blockquote>
<p>
In the next step, we will give each of them the proper positioning. </p>
<pre name="code" class="css">
	.home
	{
	background-position:0px 0px;
	width:102px;
	height:70px;
	}

	.services
	{
	background-position:-102px 0px;
	width:110px;
	height:70px
	}

	.portfolio
	{
	background-position:-212px 0px;
	width:108px;
	height:70px
	}

	.about
	{
	background-position:-320px 0px;
	width:102px;
	height:70px
	}

	.contact
	{
	background-position:-422px 0px;
	width:103px;
	height:70px
	}
</pre>
<p>Here, we&#8217;ve set the background positioning, and width of each anchor tag. The values may vary, and it requires a bit of time to get perfect.
</p>
<h3>Step 30</h3>
<pre name="code" class="css">
#navigation a .hover {
	background:url(images/sprite.jpg) no-repeat;
	display: block;
	opacity: 0;
	position: relative;
	top: 0;
	left: 0;
	height: 100%;
	width: 100%;
	}

	#navigation a.home .hover {
	background-position: -0px -72px;

	}
	#navigation a.services .hover{
	background-position: -102px -72px;

	}
	#navigation a.portfolio .hover {
	background-position: -212px -72px;
	}
	#navigation a.about .hover {
	background-position: -320px -72px;
	}
	#navigation a.contact .hover {
	background-position: -422px -72px;
	}
</pre>
<p>
Now we will define the CSS for the span; this is the same sprite image which is used above. The height and width are made 100% so that it occupies the whole anchor block. The background of each span tag is adjusted, and finally our work is complete.
</p>
<h3>Step 31</h3>
<p>Note that it takes time to get the position and width tuning right; you may end up with slightly different values for these attributes &#8211; and that&#8217;s perfectly okay! </p>
<h3>CSS Sprites Resources</h3>
<p>Phew seems like a lot of work, but great things take time to build up. Here are some additional resources that you might find handy. </p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://css-tricks.com/css-sprites/">CSS Tricks has an awesome tutorial for beginners.</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.distinctcorp.com.au/jquery/spritemenu.html"> Too tedious for you? Here&#8217;s a plugin that converts your sprite image into a menu</a>.</li>
<li><a href="http://davidwalsh.name/css-sprite-menu">A MooTools fan? Check out this neat tutorial</a>.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.csssprites.com/"> cssSprites.com</a></li>
</ul>
<ul class="webroundup">
<li>Follow us on <a href="http://www.twitter.com/nettuts">Twitter</a>, or subscribe to the <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/nettuts" title="Nettuts+ RSS Feed">Nettuts+ RSS Feed</a> for the best web development tutorials on the web.</li>
</ul>
<p>
<script type="text/javascript"><!--digg_url = "post permalink (not digg url)"; // -->
</script><br />
<script src="http://digg.com/tools/diggthis.js" type="text/javascript"></script></p>

<p><a href="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/0cOvJRjyUKXhc0rv_JtNNz0WJ3c/0/da"><img src="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/0cOvJRjyUKXhc0rv_JtNNz0WJ3c/0/di" border="0" ismap="true"></img></a><br/>
<a href="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/0cOvJRjyUKXhc0rv_JtNNz0WJ3c/1/da"><img src="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/0cOvJRjyUKXhc0rv_JtNNz0WJ3c/1/di" border="0" ismap="true"></img></a></p><div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=N8jj0wlTD6s:zQUv6yR1tyg:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=N8jj0wlTD6s:zQUv6yR1tyg:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=N8jj0wlTD6s:zQUv6yR1tyg:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=N8jj0wlTD6s:zQUv6yR1tyg:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=N8jj0wlTD6s:zQUv6yR1tyg:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=N8jj0wlTD6s:zQUv6yR1tyg:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=N8jj0wlTD6s:zQUv6yR1tyg:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=N8jj0wlTD6s:zQUv6yR1tyg:TzevzKxY174"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?d=TzevzKxY174" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/nettuts/~4/N8jj0wlTD6s" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://net.tutsplus.com/tutorials/html-css-techniques/use-sprites-to-create-an-awesomeness-filled-navigation-menu/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>78</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://net.tutsplus.com/tutorials/html-css-techniques/use-sprites-to-create-an-awesomeness-filled-navigation-menu/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>The Joy of FirePHP: A Crash-Course: New Plus Tutorial</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/nettuts/~3/rFhGwfgvTrw/</link>
		<comments>http://net.tutsplus.com/tutorials/php/the-joy-of-firephp-a-crash-course-new-plus-tutorial/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2009 00:32:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Simon Harp</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[PHP]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Plus]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[firebug]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[firefox]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[firefox extension]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[firephp]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://net.tutsplus.com/?p=8050</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<img src="http://nettutsplus.s3.amazonaws.com/42_firephp/200x200.jpg" alt="The Joy of FirePHP: A Crash-Course: New Plus Tutorial" />]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>FirePHP is a Firefox plugin and server-side library combination which allows you to send all sorts of juicy info from your web application directly to your browser, much like the console.log() functionality with JavaScript. In this PLUS tutorial and companion screencast, we&#8217;ll teach you how to get started from the very beginning! <a href="http://net.tutsplus.com/about/join-plus/">Join TUTS Plus</a>.</p>
</p>
<p><span id="more-8050"></span></p>
<div class="tutorial_image">
<a href="http://net.tutsplus.com/about/join-plus/"><br />
   <img src="http://nettutsplus.s3.amazonaws.com/42_firephp/ajax-2.png" alt="Example" style="width: 600px;" /><br />
</a>
</div>
<div class="tutorial_image">
<a href="http://net.tutsplus.com/about/join-plus/"><br />
   <img src="http://nettutsplus.s3.amazonaws.com/42_firephp/array-variable-viewer.png" alt="Example" style="width: 600px;" /><br />
</a>
</div>
<h3>Join Tuts Plus</h3>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://miscfiles.s3.amazonaws.com/banners/nettuts_468x60.jpg" border=0 alt="NETTUTS+ Screencasts and Bonus Tutorials" width=468 height=60></div>
<p>
For those unfamiliar, the family of TUTS sites runs a premium membership service called <a href="http://www.tutsplus.com">&#8220;TUTSPLUS&#8221;</a>. For $9 per month, you gain access to exclusive premium tutorials, screencasts, and freebies from <a href="http://net.tutsplus.com">Nettuts+</a>, <a href="psd.tutsplus.com">Psdtuts+</a>, <a href="ae.tutsplus.com">Aetuts+</a>, <a href="audio.tutsplus.com">Audiotuts+</a>, and <a href="vector.tutsplus.com">Vectortuts+!</a> For the price of a pizza, you&#8217;ll learn from some of the best minds in the business. <a href="http://net.tutsplus.com/about/join-plus/">Join today!</a> </p>
<ul class="webroundup">
<li>Subscribe to the <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/nettuts" title="Nettuts+ RSS Feed">Nettuts+ RSS Feed</a> for more daily web development tuts and articles.</li>
</ul>
<p>
<script type="text/javascript"><!--digg_url = "post permalink (not digg url)"; // -->
</script><br />
<script src="http://digg.com/tools/diggthis.js" type="text/javascript"></script></p>

<p><a href="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/ZPQGb-RxVVNJ5jIXpcoXqKUfOu8/0/da"><img src="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/ZPQGb-RxVVNJ5jIXpcoXqKUfOu8/0/di" border="0" ismap="true"></img></a><br/>
<a href="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/ZPQGb-RxVVNJ5jIXpcoXqKUfOu8/1/da"><img src="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/ZPQGb-RxVVNJ5jIXpcoXqKUfOu8/1/di" border="0" ismap="true"></img></a></p><div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=rFhGwfgvTrw:pBaJ1fJCI9A:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=rFhGwfgvTrw:pBaJ1fJCI9A:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=rFhGwfgvTrw:pBaJ1fJCI9A:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=rFhGwfgvTrw:pBaJ1fJCI9A:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=rFhGwfgvTrw:pBaJ1fJCI9A:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=rFhGwfgvTrw:pBaJ1fJCI9A:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=rFhGwfgvTrw:pBaJ1fJCI9A:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=rFhGwfgvTrw:pBaJ1fJCI9A:TzevzKxY174"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?d=TzevzKxY174" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/nettuts/~4/rFhGwfgvTrw" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://net.tutsplus.com/tutorials/php/the-joy-of-firephp-a-crash-course-new-plus-tutorial/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>19</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://net.tutsplus.com/tutorials/php/the-joy-of-firephp-a-crash-course-new-plus-tutorial/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>HTTP Headers for Dummies</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/nettuts/~3/dKRCkN_cJfA/</link>
		<comments>http://net.tutsplus.com/tutorials/other/http-headers-for-dummies/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2009 10:30:13 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Burak Guzel</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Other]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[error pages]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[headers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[http]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[http headers]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://net.tutsplus.com/?p=8039</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/511_http/preview.jpg" alt="HTTP Headers for Dummies" width="200" height="200"/>]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Whether you&#8217;re a programmer or not, you have seen it everywhere on the web. At this moment your browsers address bar shows something that starts with &#8220;http://&#8221;. Even your first Hello World script sent HTTP headers without you realizing it. In this article we are going to learn about the basics of HTTP headers and how we can use them in our web applications.</p>
<p><span id="more-8039"></span></p>
<h3>What are HTTP Headers?</h3>
<p>HTTP stands for &#8220;Hypertext Transfer Protocol&#8221;. The entire World Wide Web uses this protocol. It was established in the early 1990&#8217;s. Almost everything you see in your browser is transmitted to your computer over HTTP. For example, when you opened this article page, your browser probably have sent over 40 HTTP requests and received HTTP responses for each.</p>
<p>HTTP headers are the core part of these HTTP requests and responses, and they carry information about the client browser, the requested page, the server and more.</p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/511_http/http_diagram.png" border="0" /></div>
<h4>Example</h4>
<p>When you type a url in your address bar, your browser sends an HTTP request and it may look like this:</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
GET /tutorials/other/top-20-mysql-best-practices/ HTTP/1.1
Host: net.tutsplus.com
User-Agent: Mozilla/5.0 (Windows; U; Windows NT 6.1; en-US; rv:1.9.1.5) Gecko/20091102 Firefox/3.5.5 (.NET CLR 3.5.30729)
Accept: text/html,application/xhtml+xml,application/xml;q=0.9,*/*;q=0.8
Accept-Language: en-us,en;q=0.5
Accept-Encoding: gzip,deflate
Accept-Charset: ISO-8859-1,utf-8;q=0.7,*;q=0.7
Keep-Alive: 300
Connection: keep-alive
Cookie: PHPSESSID=r2t5uvjq435r4q7ib3vtdjq120
Pragma: no-cache
Cache-Control: no-cache
</pre>
<p>First line is the &#8220;Request Line&#8221; which contains some basic info on the request. And the rest are the HTTP headers.</p>
<p>After that request, your browser receives an HTTP response that may look like this:</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
HTTP/1.x 200 OK
Transfer-Encoding: chunked
Date: Sat, 28 Nov 2009 04:36:25 GMT
Server: LiteSpeed
Connection: close
X-Powered-By: W3 Total Cache/0.8
Pragma: public
Expires: Sat, 28 Nov 2009 05:36:25 GMT
Etag: "pub1259380237;gz"
Cache-Control: max-age=3600, public
Content-Type: text/html; charset=UTF-8
Last-Modified: Sat, 28 Nov 2009 03:50:37 GMT
X-Pingback: http://net.tutsplus.com/xmlrpc.php
Content-Encoding: gzip
Vary: Accept-Encoding, Cookie, User-Agent

<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Strict//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-strict.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
<meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=utf-8" />

<!-- ... rest of the html ... -->
</pre>
<p>The first line is the &#8220;Status Line&#8221;, followed by &#8220;HTTP headers&#8221;, until the blank line. After that, the &#8220;content&#8221; starts (in this case, an HTML output).</p>
<p>When you look at the source code of a web page in your browser, you will only see the HTML portion and not the HTTP headers, even though they actually have been transmitted together as you see above.</p>
<p>These HTTP requests are also sent and received for other things, such as images, CSS files, JavaScript files etc. That is why I said earlier that your browser has sent at least 40 or more HTTP requests as you loaded just this article page.</p>
<p>Now, let&#8217;s start reviewing the structure in more detail.</p>
<h3>How to See HTTP Headers</h3>
<p>I use the following Firefox extensions to analyze HTTP headers:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://getfirebug.com/">Firebug</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/511_http/firebug.png" border="0" /></div>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/3829">Live HTTP Headers</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/511_http/live_http.png" border="0" /></div>
<p>In PHP:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://php.net/manual/en/function.getallheaders.php">getallheaders()</a> gets the request headers. You can also use the $_SERVER array.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.php.net/manual/en/function.headers-list.php">headers_list()</a> gets the response headers.</li>
</ul>
<p>Further in the article, we will see some code examples in PHP.</p>
<h3>HTTP Request Structure</h3>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/511_http/request_header.png" border="0" /></div>
<p>The first line of the HTTP request is called the request line and consists of 3 parts:</p>
<ul>
<li>The &#8220;method&#8221; indicates what kind of request this is. Most common methods are GET, POST and HEAD.</li>
<li>The &#8220;path&#8221; is generally the part of the url that comes after the host (domain). For example, when requesting &#8220;http://net.tutsplus.com/tutorials/other/top-20-mysql-best-practices/&#8221; , the path portion is &#8220;/tutorials/other/top-20-mysql-best-practices/&#8221;.</li>
<li>The &#8220;protocol&#8221; part contains &#8220;HTTP&#8221; and the version, which is usually 1.1 in modern browsers.</li>
</ul>
<p>The remainder of the request contains HTTP headers as &#8220;Name: Value&#8221; pairs on each line. These contain various information about the HTTP request and your browser. For example, the &#8220;User-Agent&#8221; line provides information on the browser version and the Operating System you are using. &#8220;Accept-Encoding&#8221; tells the server if your browser can accept compressed output like gzip.</p>
<p>You may have noticed that the cookie data is also transmitted inside an HTTP header. And if there was a referring url, that would have been in the header too.</p>
<p>Most of these headers are optional. This HTTP request could have been as small as this:</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
GET /tutorials/other/top-20-mysql-best-practices/ HTTP/1.1
Host: net.tutsplus.com
</pre>
<p>And you would still get a valid response from the web server.</p>
<h3>Request Methods</h3>
<p>The three most commonly used request methods are: GET, POST and HEAD. You&#8217;re probably already familiar with the first two, from writing html forms.</p>
<h4>GET: Retrieve a Document</h4>
<p>This is the main method used for retrieving html, images, JavaScript, CSS, etc. Most data that loads in your browser was requested using this method.</p>
<p>For example, when loading a Nettuts+ article, the very first line of the HTTP request looks like so:</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
GET /tutorials/other/top-20-mysql-best-practices/ HTTP/1.1
...
</pre>
<p>Once the html loads, the browser will start sending GET request for images, that may look like this:</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
GET /wp-content/themes/tuts_theme/images/header_bg_tall.png HTTP/1.1
...
</pre>
<p>Web forms can be set to use the method GET. Here is an example.</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
&lt;form method="GET" action="foo.php">

First Name:
<input type="text" name="first_name" /> &lt;br />
Last Name:
<input type="text" name="last_name" /> &lt;br />

&lt;input type="submit" name="action" value="Submit" />

&lt;/form>
</pre>
<p>When that form is submitted, the HTTP request begins like this:</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
GET /foo.php?first_name=John&#038;last_name=Doe&#038;action=Submit HTTP/1.1
...
</pre>
<p>You can see that each form input was added into the query string.</p>
<h4>POST: Send Data to the Server</h4>
<p>Even though you can send data to the server using GET and the query string, in many cases POST will be preferable. Sending large amounts of data using GET is not practical and has limitations.</p>
<p>POST requests are most commonly sent by web forms. Let&#8217;s change the previous form example to a POST method.</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
&lt;form method="POST" action="foo.php">

First Name: &lt;input type="text" name="first_name" /> &lt;br />
Last Name: &lt;input type="text" name="last_name" /> &lt;br />

&lt;input type="submit" name="action" value="Submit" />

&lt;/form>
</pre>
<p>Submitting that form creates an HTTP request like this:</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
POST /foo.php HTTP/1.1
Host: localhost
User-Agent: Mozilla/5.0 (Windows; U; Windows NT 6.1; en-US; rv:1.9.1.5) Gecko/20091102 Firefox/3.5.5 (.NET CLR 3.5.30729)
Accept: text/html,application/xhtml+xml,application/xml;q=0.9,*/*;q=0.8
Accept-Language: en-us,en;q=0.5
Accept-Encoding: gzip,deflate
Accept-Charset: ISO-8859-1,utf-8;q=0.7,*;q=0.7
Keep-Alive: 300
Connection: keep-alive
Referer: http://localhost/test.php
Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded
Content-Length: 43

first_name=John&#038;last_name=Doe&#038;action=Submit
</pre>
<p>There are three important things to note here:</p>
<ul>
<li>The path in the first line is simply /foo.php and there is no query string anymore.</li>
<li>Content-Type and Content-Lenght headers have been added, which provide information about the data being sent.</li>
<li>All the data is in now sent after the headers, with the same format as the query string.</li>
</ul>
<p>POST method requests can also be made via AJAX, applications, cURL, etc. And all file upload forms are required to use the POST method.</p>
<h4>HEAD: Retrieve Header Information</h4>
<p>HEAD is identical to GET, except the server does not return the content in the HTTP response. When you send a HEAD request, it means that you are only interested in the response code and the HTTP headers, not the document itself.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
&#8220;When you send a HEAD request, it means that you are only interested in the response code and the HTTP headers, not the document itself.&#8221;
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>With this method the browser can check if a document has been modified, for caching purposes. It can also check if the document exists at all.</p>
<p>For example, if you have a lot of links on your website, you can periodically send HEAD requests to all of them to check for broken links. This will work much faster than using GET.</p>
<h3>HTTP Response Structure</h3>
<p>After the browser sends the HTTP request, the server responds with an HTTP response. Excluding the content, it looks like this:</p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/511_http/response_header.png" border="0" /></div>
<p>The first piece of data is the protocol. This is again usually HTTP/1.x or HTTP/1.1 on modern servers.</p>
<p>The next part is the status code followed by a short message. Code 200 means that our GET request was successful and the server will return the contents of the requested document, right after the headers.</p>
<p>We all have seen &#8220;404&#8243; pages. This number actually comes from the status code part of the HTTP response. If the GET request would be made for a path that the server cannot find, it would respond with a 404 instead of 200.</p>
<p>The rest of the response contains headers just like the HTTP request. These values can contain information about the server software, when the page/file was last modified, the mime type etc&#8230;</p>
<p>Again, most of those headers are actually optional.</p>
<h3>HTTP Status Codes</h3>
<ul>
<li>200&#8217;s are used for successful requests. </li>
<li>300&#8217;s are for redirections. </li>
<li>400&#8217;s are used if there was a problem with the request. </li>
<li>500&#8217;s are used if there was a problem with the server.</li>
</ul>
<h4>200 OK</h4>
<p>As mentioned before, this status code is sent in response to a successful request.</p>
<h4>206 Partial Content</h4>
<p>If an application requests only a range of the requested file, the 206 code is returned.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s most commonly used with download managers that can stop and resume a download, or split the download into pieces.</p>
<h4>404 Not Found</h4>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/511_http/404.png" border="0" /></div>
<p>When the requested page or file was not found, a 404 response code is sent by the server.</p>
<h4>401 Unauthorized</h4>
<p>Password protected web pages send this code. If you don&#8217;t enter a login correctly, you may see the following in your browser.</p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/511_http/401.png" border="0" /></div>
<p>Note that this only applies to HTTP password protected pages, that pop up login prompts like this:</p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/511_http/401_prompt.png" border="0" /></div>
<h4>403 Forbidden</h4>
<p>If you are not allowed to access a page, this code may be sent to your browser. This often happens when you try to open a url for a folder, that contains no index page. If the server settings do not allow the display of the folder contents, you will get a 403 error.</p>
<p>For example, on my local server I created an images folder. Inside this folder I put an .htaccess file with this line: <em>&#8220;Options -Indexes&#8221;. </em>Now when I try to open http://localhost/images/ &#8211; I see this:</p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/511_http/403.png" border="0" /></div>
<p>There are other ways in which access can be blocked, and 403 can be sent. For example, you can block by IP address, with the help of some htaccess directives.</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
order allow,deny
deny from 192.168.44.201
deny from 224.39.163.12
deny from 172.16.7.92
allow from all
</pre>
<h4>302 (or 307) Moved Temporarily &#038; 301 Moved Permanently</h4>
<p>These two codes are used for redirecting a browser. For example, when you use a url shortening service, such as <a href="http://bit.ly">bit.ly</a>, that&#8217;s exactly how they forward the people who click on their links.</p>
<p>Both 302 and 301 are handled very similarly by the browser, but they can have different meanings to search engine spiders. For instance, if your website is down for maintenance, you may redirect to another location using 302. The search engine spider will continue checking your page later in the future. But if you redirect using 301, it will tell the spider that your website has moved to that location permanently. To give you a better idea: http://www.nettuts.com redirects to http://net.tutsplus.com/ using a 301 code instead of 302.</p>
<h4>500 Internal Server Error</h4>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/511_http/500.png" border="0" /></div>
<p>This code is usually seen when a web script crashes. Most CGI scripts do not output errors directly to the browser, unlike PHP. If there is any fatal errors, they will just send a 500 status code. And the programmer then needs to search the server error logs to find the error messages.</p>
<h4>Complete List</h4>
<p>You can find the complete list of HTTP status codes with their explanations <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_HTTP_status_codes">here</a>.</p>
<h3>HTTP Headers in HTTP Requests</h3>
<p>Now, we&#8217;ll review some of the most common HTTP headers found in HTTP requests.</p>
<p>Almost all of these headers can be found in the $_SERVER array in PHP. You can also use the <a href="http://php.net/manual/en/function.getallheaders.php">getallheaders()</a> function to retrieve all headers at once.</p>
<h4>Host</h4>
<p>An HTTP Request is sent to a specific IP Addresses. But since most servers are capable of hosting multiple websites under the same IP, they must know which domain name the browser is looking for.</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
Host: net.tutsplus.com
</pre>
<p>This is basically the host name, including the domain and the subdomain.</p>
<p>In PHP, it can be found as $_SERVER['HTTP_HOST'] or $_SERVER['SERVER_NAME'].</p>
<h4>User-Agent</h4>
<pre name="code" class="html">
User-Agent: Mozilla/5.0 (Windows; U; Windows NT 6.1; en-US; rv:1.9.1.5) Gecko/20091102 Firefox/3.5.5 (.NET CLR 3.5.30729)
</pre>
<p>This header can carry several pieces of information such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Browser name and version.</li>
<li>Operating System name and version.</li>
<li>Default language.</li>
</ul>
<p>This is how websites can collect certain general information about their surfers&#8217; systems. For example, they can detect if the surfer is using a cell phone browser and redirect them to a mobile version of their website which works better with low resolutions.</p>
<p>In PHP, it can be found with: $_SERVER['HTTP_USER_AGENT'].</p>
<pre name="code" class="php">
if ( strstr($_SERVER['HTTP_USER_AGENT'],'MSIE 6') ) {
	echo "Please stop using IE6!";
}
</pre>
<h4>Accept-Language</h4>
<pre name="code" class="html">
Accept-Language: en-us,en;q=0.5
</pre>
<p>This header displays the default language setting of the user. If a website has different language versions, it can redirect a new surfer based on this data.</p>
<p>It can carry multiple languages, separated by commas. The first one is the preferred language, and each other listed language can carry a &#8220;q&#8221; value, which is an estimate of the user&#8217;s preference for the language (min. 0 max. 1).</p>
<p>In PHP, it can be found as: $_SERVER["HTTP_ACCEPT_LANGUAGE"].</p>
<pre name="code" class="php">
if (substr($_SERVER['HTTP_ACCEPT_LANGUAGE'], 0, 2) == 'fr') {
	header('Location: http://french.mydomain.com');
}
</pre>
<h4>Accept-Encoding</h4>
<pre name="code" class="html">
Accept-Encoding: gzip,deflate
</pre>
<p>Most modern browsers support gzip, and will send this in the header. The web server then can send the HTML output in a compressed format. This can reduce the size by up to 80% to save bandwidth and time.</p>
<p>In PHP, it can be found as:  $_SERVER["HTTP_ACCEPT_ENCODING"]. However, when you use the <a href="http://www.php.net/manual/en/function.ob-gzhandler.php">ob_gzhandler()</a> callback function, it will check this value automatically, so you don&#8217;t need to.</p>
<pre name="code" class="php">
// enables output buffering
// and all output is compressed if the browser supports it
ob_start('ob_gzhandler');
</pre>
<h4>If-Modified-Since</h4>
<p>If a web document is already cached in your browser, and you visit it again, your browser can check if the document has been updated by sending this:</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
If-Modified-Since: Sat, 28 Nov 2009 06:38:19 GMT
</pre>
<p>If it was not modified since that date, the server will send a &#8220;304 Not Modified&#8221; response code, and no content &#8211; and the browser will load the content from the cache.</p>
<p>In PHP, it can be found as: $_SERVER['HTTP_IF_MODIFIED_SINCE'].</p>
<pre name="code" class="php">
// assume $last_modify_time was the last the output was updated

// did the browser send If-Modified-Since header?
if(isset($_SERVER['HTTP_IF_MODIFIED_SINCE'])) {

	// if the browser cache matches the modify time
	if ($last_modify_time == strtotime($_SERVER['HTTP_IF_MODIFIED_SINCE'])) {

		// send a 304 header, and no content
		header("HTTP/1.1 304 Not Modified");
		exit;
	}

}
</pre>
<p>There is also an HTTP header named Etag, which can be used to make sure the cache is current. We&#8217;ll talk about this shortly. </p>
<h4>Cookie</h4>
<p>As the name suggests, this sends the cookies stored in your browser for that domain.</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
Cookie: PHPSESSID=r2t5uvjq435r4q7ib3vtdjq120; foo=bar
</pre>
<p>These are name=value pairs separated by semicolons. Cookies can also contain the session id.</p>
<p>In PHP, individual cookies can be accessed with the $_COOKIE array. You can directly access the session variables using the $_SESSION array, and if you need the session id, you can use the session_id() function instead of the cookie.</p>
<pre name="code" class="php">
echo $_COOKIE['foo'];
// output: bar
echo $_COOKIE['PHPSESSID'];
// output: r2t5uvjq435r4q7ib3vtdjq120
session_start();
echo session_id();
// output: r2t5uvjq435r4q7ib3vtdjq120
</pre>
<h4>Referer</h4>
<p>As the name suggests, this HTTP header contains the referring url.</p>
<p>For example, if I visit the Nettuts+ homepage, and click on an article link, this header is sent to my browser:</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
Referer: http://net.tutsplus.com/
</pre>
<p>In PHP, it can be found as $_SERVER['HTTP_REFERER'].</p>
<pre name="code" class="php">
if (isset($_SERVER['HTTP_REFERER'])) {

	$url_info = parse_url($_SERVER['HTTP_REFERER']);

	// is the surfer coming from Google?
	if ($url_info['host'] == 'www.google.com') {

		parse_str($url_info['query'], $vars);

		echo "You searched on Google for this keyword: ". $vars['q'];

	}

}
// if the referring url was:
// http://www.google.com/search?source=ig&#038;hl=en&#038;rlz=&#038;=&#038;q=http+headers&#038;aq=f&#038;oq=&#038;aqi=g-p1g9
// the output will be:
// You searched on Google for this keyword: http headers
</pre>
<p>You may have noticed the word &#8220;referrer&#8221; is misspelled as &#8220;referer&#8221;. Unfortunately it made into the official HTTP specifications like that and got stuck.</p>
<h4>Authorization</h4>
<p>When a web page asks for authorization, the browser opens a login window. When you enter a username and password in this window, the browser sends another HTTP request, but this time it contains this header.</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
Authorization: Basic bXl1c2VyOm15cGFzcw==
</pre>
<p>The data inside the header is base64 encoded. For example, base64_decode(&#8217;bXl1c2VyOm15cGFzcw==&#8217;) would return &#8216;myuser:mypass&#8217;</p>
<p>In PHP, these values can be found as $_SERVER['PHP_AUTH_USER'] and $_SERVER['PHP_AUTH_PW'].</p>
<p>More on this when we talk about the WWW-Authenticate header.</p>
<h3>HTTP Headers in HTTP Responses</h3>
<p>Now we are going to look at some of the most common HTTP headers found in HTTP responses.</p>
<p>In PHP, you can set response headers using the <a href="http://php.net/manual/en/function.header.php">header()</a> function. PHP already sends certain headers automatically, for loading the content and setting cookies etc&#8230; You can see the headers that are sent, or will be sent, with the <a href="http://www.php.net/manual/en/function.headers-list.php">headers_list()</a> function. You can check if the headers have been sent already, with the <a href="http://www.php.net/manual/en/function.headers-sent.php">headers_sent()</a> function.</p>
<h4>Cache-Control</h4>
<p>Definition from w3.org: &#8220;The Cache-Control general-header field is used to specify directives which MUST be obeyed by all caching mechanisms along the request/response chain.&#8221; These &#8220;caching mechanisms&#8221; include gateways and proxies that your ISP may be using.</p>
<p>Example:</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
Cache-Control: max-age=3600, public
</pre>
<p>&#8220;public&#8221; means that the response may be cached by anyone. &#8220;max-age&#8221; indicates how many seconds the cache is valid for. Allowing your website to be cached can reduce server load and bandwidth, and also improve load times at the browser.</p>
<p>Caching can also be prevented by using the &#8220;no-cache&#8221; directive.</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
Cache-Control: no-cache
</pre>
<p>For more detailed info, see <a href="http://www.w3.org/Protocols/rfc2616/rfc2616-sec14.html#sec14.9">w3.org</a>.</p>
<h4>Content-Type</h4>
<p>This header indicates the &#8220;mime-type&#8221; of the document. The browser then decides how to interpret the contents based on this. For example, an html page (or a PHP script with html output) may return this:</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
Content-Type: text/html; charset=UTF-8
</pre>
<p>&#8220;text&#8221; is the type and &#8220;html&#8221; is the subtype of the document. The header can also contain more info such as charset.</p>
<p>For a gif image, this may be sent.</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
Content-Type: image/gif
</pre>
<p>The browser can decide to use an external application or browser extension based on the mime-type. For example this will cause the Adobe Reader to be loaded:</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
Content-Type: application/pdf
</pre>
<p>When loading directly, Apache can usually detect the mime-type of a document and send the appropriate header. Also most browsers have some amount fault tolerance and auto-detection of the mime-types, in case the headers are wrong or not present.</p>
<p>You can find a list of common mime types <a href="http://www.webmaster-toolkit.com/mime-types.shtml">here</a>.</p>
<p>In PHP, you can use the <a href="http://www.php.net/manual/en/function.finfo-file.php">finfo_file()</a> function to detect the mime type of a file.</p>
<h4>Content-Disposition</h4>
<p>This header instructs the browser to open a file download box, instead of trying to parse the content. Example:</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
Content-Disposition: attachment; filename="download.zip"
</pre>
<p>That will cause the browser to do this:</p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/511_http/download.png" border="0" /></div>
<p>Note that the appropriate Content-Type header should also be sent along with this:</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
Content-Type: application/zip
Content-Disposition: attachment; filename="download.zip"
</pre>
<h4>Content-Length</h4>
<p>When content is going to be transmitted to the browser, the server can indicate the size of it (in bytes) using this header.</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
Content-Length: 89123
</pre>
<p>This is especially useful for file downloads. That&#8217;s how the browser can determine the progress of the download.</p>
<p>For example, here is a dummy script I wrote, which simulates a slow download.</p>
<pre name="code" class="php">
// it's a zip file
header('Content-Type: application/zip');
// 1 million bytes (about 1megabyte)
header('Content-Length: 1000000');
// load a download dialogue, and save it as download.zip
header('Content-Disposition: attachment; filename="download.zip"');

// 1000 times 1000 bytes of data
for ($i = 0; $i < 1000; $i++) {
	echo str_repeat(".",1000);

	// sleep to slow down the download
	usleep(50000);
}
</pre>
<p>The result is:</p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/511_http/download_with_progress.png" border="0" /></div>
<p>Now I am going to comment out the Content-Length header</p>
<pre name="code" class="php">
// it's a zip file
header('Content-Type: application/zip');
// the browser won't know the size
// header('Content-Length: 1000000');
// load a download dialogue, and save it as download.zip
header('Content-Disposition: attachment; filename="download.zip"');

// 1000 times 1000 bytes of data
for ($i = 0; $i < 1000; $i++) {
	echo str_repeat(".",1000);

	// sleep to slow down the download
	usleep(50000);
}
</pre>
<p>Now the result is:</p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/511_http/download_without_progress.png" border="0" /></div>
<p>The browser can only tell you how many bytes have been downloaded, but it does not know the total amount. And the progress bar is not showing the progress.</p>
<h4>Etag</h4>
<p>This is another header that is used for caching purposes. It looks like this:</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
Etag: "pub1259380237;gz"
</pre>
<p>The web server may send this header with every document it serves. The value can be based on the last modify date, file size or even the checksum value of a file. The browser then saves this value as it caches the document. Next time the browser requests the same file, it sends this in the HTTP request:</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
If-None-Match: "pub1259380237;gz"
</pre>
<p>If the Etag value of the document matches that, the server will send a 304 code instead of 200, and no content. The browser will load the contents from its cache.</p>
<h4>Last-Modified</h4>
<p>As the name suggests, this header indicates the last modify date of the document, in GMT format:</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
Last-Modified: Sat, 28 Nov 2009 03:50:37 GMT
</pre>
<pre name="code" class="php">
$modify_time = filemtime($file);

header("Last-Modified: " . gmdate("D, d M Y H:i:s", $modify_time) . " GMT");
</pre>
<p>It offers another way for the browser to cache a document. The browser may send this in the HTTP request:</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
If-Modified-Since: Sat, 28 Nov 2009 06:38:19 GMT
</pre>
<p>We already talked about this earlier in the "If-Modified-Since" section.</p>
<h4>Location</h4>
<p>This header is used for redirections. If the response code is 301 or 302, the server must also send this header. For example, when you go to http://www.nettuts.com your browser will receive this:</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
HTTP/1.x 301 Moved Permanently
...
Location: http://net.tutsplus.com/
...
</pre>
<p>In PHP, you can redirect a surfer like so:</p>
<pre name="code" class="php">
header('Location: http://net.tutsplus.com/');
</pre>
<p>By default, that will send a 302 response code. If you want to send 301 instead:</p>
<pre name="code" class="php">
header('Location: http://net.tutsplus.com/', true, 301);
</pre>
<h4>Set-Cookie</h4>
<p>When a website wants to set or update a cookie in your browser, it will use this header.</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
Set-Cookie: skin=noskin; path=/; domain=.amazon.com; expires=Sun, 29-Nov-2009 21:42:28 GMT
Set-Cookie: session-id=120-7333518-8165026; path=/; domain=.amazon.com; expires=Sat Feb 27 08:00:00 2010 GMT
</pre>
<p>Each cookie is sent as a separate header. Note that the cookies set via JavaScript do not go through HTTP headers.</p>
<p>In PHP, you can set cookies using the <a href="http://php.net/manual/en/function.setcookie.php">setcookie()</a> function, and PHP sends the appropriate HTTP headers.</p>
<pre name="code" class="php">
setcookie("TestCookie", "foobar");
</pre>
<p>Which causes this header to be sent:</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
Set-Cookie: TestCookie=foobar
</pre>
<p>If the expiration date is not specified, the cookie is deleted when the browser window is closed.</p>
<h4>WWW-Authenticate</h4>
<p>A website may send this header to authenticate a user through HTTP. When the browser sees this header, it will open up a login dialogue window.</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
WWW-Authenticate: Basic realm="Restricted Area"
</pre>
<p>Which looks like this:</p>
<div class="tutorial_image"><img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/511_http/401_prompt.png" border="0" /></div>
<p>There is a <a href="http://php.net/manual/en/features.http-auth.php">section</a> in the PHP manual, that has code samples on how to do this in PHP.</p>
<pre name="code" class="php">
if (!isset($_SERVER['PHP_AUTH_USER'])) {
    header('WWW-Authenticate: Basic realm="My Realm"');
    header('HTTP/1.0 401 Unauthorized');
    echo 'Text to send if user hits Cancel button';
    exit;
} else {
    echo "

Hello {$_SERVER['PHP_AUTH_USER']}.

";
    echo "

You entered {$_SERVER['PHP_AUTH_PW']} as your password.

";
}
</pre>
<h4>Content-Encoding</h4>
<p>This header is usually set when the returned content is compressed.</p>
<pre name="code" class="html">
Content-Encoding: gzip
</pre>
<p>In PHP, if you use the <a href="http://www.php.net/manual/en/function.ob-gzhandler.php">ob_gzhandler()</a> callback function, it will be set automatically for you.</p>
<h3>Conclusion</h3>
<p>Thanks for reading. I hope this article was a good starting point to learn about HTTP Headers. Please leave your comments and questions below, and I will try to respond as much as I can.</p>

<p><a href="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/Nad84Pk3LOfRtwelHAKk0HKDZjE/0/da"><img src="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/Nad84Pk3LOfRtwelHAKk0HKDZjE/0/di" border="0" ismap="true"></img></a><br/>
<a href="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/Nad84Pk3LOfRtwelHAKk0HKDZjE/1/da"><img src="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/Nad84Pk3LOfRtwelHAKk0HKDZjE/1/di" border="0" ismap="true"></img></a></p><div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=dKRCkN_cJfA:aBIc1jDtjjM:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=dKRCkN_cJfA:aBIc1jDtjjM:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=dKRCkN_cJfA:aBIc1jDtjjM:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=dKRCkN_cJfA:aBIc1jDtjjM:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=dKRCkN_cJfA:aBIc1jDtjjM:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=dKRCkN_cJfA:aBIc1jDtjjM:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=dKRCkN_cJfA:aBIc1jDtjjM:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=dKRCkN_cJfA:aBIc1jDtjjM:TzevzKxY174"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?d=TzevzKxY174" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/nettuts/~4/dKRCkN_cJfA" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://net.tutsplus.com/tutorials/other/http-headers-for-dummies/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>52</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://net.tutsplus.com/tutorials/other/http-headers-for-dummies/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Digging into WordPress Review, and Free Copies: Winners Announced!</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/nettuts/~3/gCIAI2gfqkc/</link>
		<comments>http://net.tutsplus.com/articles/reviews/digging-into-wordpress-review-and-free-copies/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2009 17:11:13 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jeffrey Way</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[book review]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Freebies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[review]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wordpress]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://net.tutsplus.com/?p=8005</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/509_wp/book-cover.png" alt="Digging into WordPress Review, and Free Copies!" />]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
A couple weeks ago, I received an email from Chris Coyier, of <a href="http://www.css-tricks.com">CSS-Tricks</a>, containing a review copy of his recently released &#8220;<a href="https://www.e-junkie.com/ecom/gb.php?cl=88539&#038;c=ib&#038;aff=28697" target="ejejcsingle">Digging into WordPress</a>&#8221; e-book. Expecting it to be more of a mini-book, I nonchalantly told him that I&#8217;d post a review that Friday; little did I know that this was a full-fledged book, packed full of knowledge.
</p>
<p><span id="more-8005"></span></p>
<h3>Update: Winners Announced</h3>
<p>Congratulations to the following three readers who were randomly selected! </p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.kajrietberg.nl/">Kaj Rietberg</a></li>
<li><a href="http://thwdg.com/">Rodrigo Flores</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.offdutygamers.com/">Mark Christianson</a></li>
</ul>
<p><em>If your name is listed above, please contact nettuts@tutsplus.com to claim your prize!</em> </p>
<blockquote>
<p>
&#8220;Written by WordPress veterans Chris Coyier and <a href="http://www.perishablepress.com">Jeff Starr</a>, Digging into WordPress is 400+ jam-packed pages of everything you need to get the most out of WordPress. WordPress is great right out of the box, but unless you want an ordinary vanilla blog, it is essential to understand the full potential of WordPress and have the right tools to get the job done.&#8221; </p>
</blockquote>
<div class="tutorial_image">
<a href="https://www.e-junkie.com/ecom/gb.php?cl=88539&#038;c=ib&#038;aff=28697" target="ejejcsingle"><br />
<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/509_wp/book-cover.png" alt="Digging into WordPress" /><br />
</a>
</div>
<p>
Those of you who read <a href="http://www.css-tricks.com">CSS-Tricks</a> will be well aware that Chris writes in a very easy-to-understand fashion. Rather than flooding each article with high-level jargon that only the most knowledgeable of us can understand, he instead dumbs each article down to the fundamentals &#8211; even to the point of being honest enough to convey when he doesn&#8217;t quite understand the reasoning behind some line of code.
</p>
<p>
As a result, he&#8217;s built a wonderful community and reputation for himself in the last few years. This book, co-written with <a href="http://www.perishablepress.com">Jeff Starr</a>, is no different: straight-forward, easy-to-understand, and simple.
</p>
<h3>Simple Learning</h3>
<p>
Thanks to the use of fun, and helpful illustrations, even those who are brand new to WordPress will be able to <strong>dig</strong> their heals in &#8212; with minimal confusion.
</p>
<p>
The 400 page <a href="https://www.e-junkie.com/ecom/gb.php?cl=88539&#038;c=ib&#038;aff=28697" target="ejejcsingle">ebook </a>covers everything from navigating the admin panel, to creating a comments form, to even more advanced topics like plugin development. And though it&#8217;s generally good practice to point out a few negatives in one&#8217;s review, it&#8217;s difficult to do so when a book is such a pleasure to read.
</p>
<h3>Heart of a Teacher</h3>
<p>
Chris and Jeff, in this book, have proven that they have the hearts of teachers. Even for intermediate to advanced WordPressers, there&#8217;s something to be learned &#8212; and at $27, the purchase is a no-brainer!
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
&#8220;Digging into WordPress is perfect for WordPress users in the beginner to intermediate range, but contains plenty of great information for the advanced user as well. If you have any level of experience working with web design or WordPress, this book is written to help you take WordPress to the next level.&#8221;
</p>
</blockquote>
<h3>400 Pages of Practical Information</h3>
<p>&#8220;There is much to learn about the World&#8217;s most popular publishing platform.<br />
	       From your first steps of learning about WordPress all the way through<br />
	       maintaining a site throughout the years, this book is packed with truly<br />
	       practical information.&#8221;</p>
<h3>Lots of Code Samples</h3>
<p>&#8220;We go into depth about the anatomy of a WordPress theme. How they work, and how<br />
	       to write the code you need to do the things you want. This means real code that<br />
	       you can sink your teeth into, as well as copy and paste. Beyond theme<br />
	       building, we introduce many tricks your functions.php file can pull off and show<br />
	       you ways to increase performance and security through HTAccess.&#8221;</p>
<h3>What About the Free Copies!? </h3>
<div class="tutorial_image">
<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/509_wp/digwp-468-60-01.jpg" alt="Digging into WordPress Review, and Free Copies!" />
</div>
<p>
Chris has generously offered to give away a few copies to our community. <strong>To enter, simply leave a comment, and be sure to check back on Friday to see if you were randomly chosen! </strong>
</p>
<ul class="webroundup">
<li>Follow us on <a href="http://www.twitter.com/nettuts">Twitter</a>, or subscribe to the <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/nettuts" title="Nettuts+ RSS Feed">Nettuts+ RSS Feed</a> for the best web development tutorials on the web.</li>
</ul>
<p>
<script type="text/javascript"><!--digg_url = "post permalink (not digg url)"; // -->
</script><br />
<script src="http://digg.com/tools/diggthis.js" type="text/javascript"></script></p>

<p><a href="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/5ezgX4cqELbAVZgjGdEH1pmd_aI/0/da"><img src="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/5ezgX4cqELbAVZgjGdEH1pmd_aI/0/di" border="0" ismap="true"></img></a><br/>
<a href="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/5ezgX4cqELbAVZgjGdEH1pmd_aI/1/da"><img src="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/5ezgX4cqELbAVZgjGdEH1pmd_aI/1/di" border="0" ismap="true"></img></a></p><div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=gCIAI2gfqkc:oXmKIq-vNoM:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=gCIAI2gfqkc:oXmKIq-vNoM:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=gCIAI2gfqkc:oXmKIq-vNoM:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=gCIAI2gfqkc:oXmKIq-vNoM:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=gCIAI2gfqkc:oXmKIq-vNoM:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=gCIAI2gfqkc:oXmKIq-vNoM:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=gCIAI2gfqkc:oXmKIq-vNoM:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=gCIAI2gfqkc:oXmKIq-vNoM:TzevzKxY174"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?d=TzevzKxY174" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/nettuts/~4/gCIAI2gfqkc" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://net.tutsplus.com/articles/reviews/digging-into-wordpress-review-and-free-copies/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1079</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://net.tutsplus.com/articles/reviews/digging-into-wordpress-review-and-free-copies/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>50 Helpful iPhone Apps for Web Designers and Developers</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/nettuts/~3/OzHUFqmZn8U/</link>
		<comments>http://net.tutsplus.com/articles/web-roundups/50-helpful-iphone-apps-for-web-designers-and-developers/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2009 10:30:57 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jarel Remick</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Web Roundups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[iphone]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[iphone apps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mobile]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://net.tutsplus.com/?p=7966</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/200x200.jpg" alt="50 Helpful iPhone Apps for Web Designers and Developers" />]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Nearing in on 100K (Apple approved) available apps as of this writing, the iPhone is the &#8220;do anything&#8221; device that&#8217;s ready and capable of near desktop computing in the palm of your hand with the convenience of fitting in your pocket. For web designers and developers, this means no more toting around a laptop just to take care of the small bits of our job. From work to play and everything in between, the iPhone probably has you covered. As the saying goes, &#8220;Yup, there&#8217;s an app for that&#8221;.</p>
<p>I&#8217;ve listed 50 iPhone apps for all you web designers and developers which covers everything from color scheme creators and font manuals to FTP and SSH clients. Also keep in mind there are many more of the same type of app.</p>
<p><span id="more-7966"></span></p>
<style>
.postimage {
float: left;
margin-right: 2em;
margin-bottom: 2.7em; 
}</p>
</style>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=291725775&amp;mt=8">cliqcliq Colors</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/cliqcliq.jpg" alt="cliqcliq Colors" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>With cliqcliq&#8217;s Colors app, you can easily create, convert and manage colors and palettes. The app allows conversion between RGB, HSB and Grayscale. You can also extract colors and palettes from photos you&#8217;ve snapped or imported into your photo library.</p>
<p>When you&#8217;re done, you can email the palettes to yourself or someone else to quickly import into Photoshop or Illustrator.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $2.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.cliqcliq.com">cliqcliq</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=291725775&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=292243338&amp;mt=8">Color Expert</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/ColorExpert.jpg" alt="Color Expert" width="200" height="288" />
</div>
<p>Color Expert gives you an easy to use color wheel for creating great color palettes but also lets you get colors from photos, sliders and swatches. You can easily search through Pantone, web safe or HTML colors to find just what you&#8217;re looking for.</p>
<p>When you&#8217;re done, save or send the palette as an Adobe Swatch Exchange file (ASE) for Photoshop or another Adobe app.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $9.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.code-line.com/software/">Code Line</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=292243338&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=304619720&amp;mt=8">HEX RGB Colors Guide</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/HEXRGBColorGuide.jpg" alt="HEX RGB Colors Guide" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>HEX RGB Colors Guide is a pretty basic app for having a RGB and HEX color code reference guide in your pocket at all times. Choose between block or list view and get quick access to the color information you need right away.</p>
<p>For the price vs features, this is a bit spendy but could be very handy for some designers.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $3.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.insideroot.com">Inside Root Media</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=304619720&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=291340682&amp;mt=8">HTML Colors</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/HTMLColors.jpg" alt="HTML Colors" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>Quickly select and preview colors for the web with HTML Colors for some fun exploring or just to make sure you have the right combination. The sample text and background color make it easy to get the right foreground and background color combination.</p>
<p>You can also view HTML safe colors or try your luck with the &#8220;Random&#8221; button, then save or send your palette.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $0.99
<li>Developer: <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewArtist?id=291332714">Kevin White</a> (iTunes Link)</li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=291340682&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=304304134&amp;mt=8">WhatTheFont</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/WhatTheFont.jpg" alt="WhatTheFont" width="200" height="288" />
</div>
<p>You&#8217;re probably familiar with <a href="http://new.myfonts.com/WhatTheFont/">MyFont&#8217;s WhatTheFont</a> service. This app connects to that service for font discovery anywhere. Take a photo of the font (magazine, book or computer screen) or use an iPhone screenshot and WhatTheFont will tell you what the font is in just a few seconds, then view the font details within the app.</p>
<p>You never know when you&#8217;ll see a font you like or what and you it&#8217;s hard to beat free!</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: Free</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://new.myfonts.com">MyFonts</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=304304134&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=298268157&amp;mt=8">FontShuffle</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/FontShop.jpg" alt="FontShuffle" width="200" height="288" />
</div>
<p>Need typographic inspiration? FontShuffle might be your solution. Browse 650+ font families or shake your iPhone for FontShuffle to mix new fonts into your results. Browse by category or search for something more specific, then view up to 24 similar typefaces in a list.</p>
<p>Once you&#8217;ve found something you like, you can preview it with custom sample text. You can also check out the font&#8217;s glyph set.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: Free</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.fontshop.com">FontShop AG</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=298268157&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=321091154&amp;mt=8">The Typography Manual</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/TheTypographyManual.jpg" alt="The Typography Manual" width="200" height="288" />
</div>
<p>Interested in learning about typography? Or maybe just more about it? This is the app for that. It includes 60+ pages on the history of type, type basics, the latest info. on web typography and more. It doesn&#8217;t stop there though, it also has a 100+ page glossary of type terminology and examples.</p>
<p>There&#8217;s a lot more included in this app and it really is one of the best ways to learn typography.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $3.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://typographyapp.com">The Typography Manual</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=321091154&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=331975235&amp;mt=8">Photoshop.com Mobile</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/Photoshop.jpg" alt="Photoshop" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>This is the mobile companion to Photoshop.com for the iPhone which gives you access to your Photoshop.com photos for editing, uploading and sharing. Your editing capabilities are somewhat limited but considering this is on your phone, it&#8217;s quite nice.</p>
<p>You can crop and rotate, adjust color, saturation and exposure or apply filters like Sketch or Soft Focus along with many more options. It&#8217;s basic but powerful for a handheld device.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: Free</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.adobe.com">Adobe Systems Incorporated</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=331975235&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=325758140&amp;mt=8">Convert ~ the unit calculator</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/Convert.jpg" alt="Convert" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>Convert is an easy to use unit converter that even web designers and developers will want. It includes conversions all the usual stuff like volume, angles and money but also for typography, pixels, picas and a lot more.</p>
<p>It also includes a regular calculator though so you won&#8217;t need to use the iPhone&#8217;s included calculator any more.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $1.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://taptaptap.com">tap tap tap</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=325758140&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=289310044&amp;mt=8">Caliper</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/Caliper.jpg" alt="Caliper" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>Caliper is a basic but very handy app to have in your toolbox. With it you can quickly and precisely measure objects (placed on or near the screen) or images on screen in pixels, centimeters, inches and more. The measurement jaws are also multitouch for faster measuring.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $0.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.simpleyetsound.com/iPhone_Apps.html">Silverview Consulting Inc.</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=289310044&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=308126298&amp;mt=8">Source Viewer</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/SourceViewer.jpg" alt="Source Viewer" width="200" height="288" />
</div>
<p>Source Viewer does exactly what it sounds like. It lets you view the source code of websites. However, it does much more such as syntax coloring with links highlighted specially, link extraction to easily view website resources, image collection for separate viewing and much more.</p>
<p>You can also open resource URL&#8217;s via browser or send them via email, save bookmarks and toggle source code word wrap. This is a great one for developers on the go!</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $0.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://piet.jonas.com">Piet Jonas</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=308126298&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=313833572&amp;mt=8">Web Source Viewer</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/WebSourceViewer.jpg" alt="Web Source Viewer" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>Web Source Viewer is a much more basic than Source Viewer but it&#8217;s a fast and free way to view source code of any website from your iPhone.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: Free</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewArtist?id=300836795">Casey Jones</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=313833572&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=286479936&amp;mt=8">FTP On The Go</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/FTPOnTheGo.jpg" alt="FTP On The Go" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>FTP On The Go is a fully featured FTP app for the iPhone. It lets you do just about everything your desktop application does but with the convenience of mobility. Browse, upload, download, edit and preview files on your FTP or even on your iPhone. You can even email files, view documents within the app like Word, Excel, PDF&#8217;s, etc. and much more.</p>
<p>There are far too many features to list but this is a fantastic app for the price so check it out.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $6.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://ftponthego.com">Headlight Software, Inc.</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=286479936&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=302133974&amp;mt=8">ServersMan</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/ServersMan.jpg" alt="ServersMan" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>ServersMan essentially lets you use your iPhone like a wireless USB flash drive&#8230; or web server. Yeah, you can actually run a website with ServersMan. You can also store files on your iPhone via WiFi or 3G from any internet connected computer with a browser.</p>
<p>You&#8217;ll also be able to open files like Microsoft Office (Word, Excel, PowerPoint), iWork (Pages, Numbers, Keynote), PDF&#8217;s, HTML, CSS and much more.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: Free</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://serversman.com/index_en.jsp">FreeBit Co., Ltd.</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=302133974&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=286623227&amp;mt=8">TouchTerm SSH</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/TouchTermSSH.jpg" alt="TouchTerm SSH" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>If you&#8217;re looking for a full SSH terminal app, this is it. Access your servers via WiFi, 3G or EDGE with just about all the features you&#8217;d find in a desktop SSH terminal application. If you need a step up, there is also TouchTerm SSH Pro with some more advanced features optimizing usage on the iPhone.</p>
<p>With the Pro version you get features like gestures, auto-completion, graphical filesystem navigation and much, much more.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $3.99 &#8211; Pro: $8.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.ajidev.com">Aji, LLC</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=286623227&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a> &#8211; <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=296468040&amp;mt=8">Download Pro from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=312061860&amp;mt=8">DatabaseViewer</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/DatabaseViewer.jpg" alt="DatabaseViewer" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>DatabaseViewer gives you mobile access to your databases and the tools you need to work with them. It supports MySQL, PostgreSQL, MS Access, MS Excel, Oracle and several more. Sync database data via 3G, EDGE or WiFi, apply SQL Select queries, filters and much more.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s a little bit expensive, but if you need access to your databases on the go, this is a solid choice.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $19.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://cellica.com/products.html?iPhone">Cellica Corporation</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=312061860&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=304669956&amp;mt=8">Are My Sites Up</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/AreMySitesUp.jpg" alt="Are My Sites Up" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>If you run or host several websites, especially for clients, it&#8217;s important to keep an eye on their status. If you use the <a href="http://aremysitesup.com">Are My Sites Up?</a> service, this task is a breeze. This is the accompanying iPhone app for both subscription based and free versions of the service.</p>
<p>From the app you can manage account settings like email and SMS alerts, view your sites&#8217; status and get push alerts.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: Free &#8211; Lite: Free</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://shiftedfrequency.net">Shiftedfrequency</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=304669956&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a> &#8211; <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=319961348&amp;mt=8">Download Lite from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=304049591&amp;mt=8">SEO IT</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/SEOIT.jpg" alt="SEO IT" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>With SEO IT you can easily analyze a website&#8217;s Search Engine Optimization. The application will analyze tons different parts including complete source code listing, META tags, tag counts, title contents, back links and many more parts of your website of choice.</p>
<p>Curious about your competition? This is a great way to check them out. <img src='http://net.tutsplus.com/wp-includes/images/smilies/icon_wink.gif' alt=';-)' class='wp-smiley' /> </p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $0.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.infinidigm.com/proseoiphone.html">Infinidigm, Inc.</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=304049591&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=289197496&amp;mt=8">Web Tools</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/WebTools.jpg" alt="Web Tools" width="200" height="288" />
</div>
<p>With Web Tools you can check whois information, domain availability, view server information, check response times and more. When you find information you want to keep for later or share, you can email the results.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s a pretty basic app but very useful, especially if you&#8217;re with a client who&#8217;s looking for a domain.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $1.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewArtist?id=287311811">James Clark</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=289197496&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=303367437&amp;mt=8">Nomina</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/Nomina.jpg" alt="Nomina" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>Nomina does more than just check domain availability. It can pull up a lot of helpful information for building a brand such as trademark checking, common-law usage, relevance of the brand name and lots more. It&#8217;ll save you tons of time when trying to build a brand for you or your client.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $14.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.outspring.com">Outspring, Inc.</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=303367437&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=303034517&amp;mt=8">iStat &#8211; Sys Monitoring, Battery</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/iStat.jpg" alt="iStat" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>iStat gives you a great set of tools to monitor iPhone resource usage (including battery) as well as resource usage on remote systems including Mac, Linux and Solaris. You also get network tools such as ping and traceroute. Unfortunately Apple requested that they remove the &#8220;Free Memory&#8221; feature, which many are not happy about.</p>
<p>Easily monitor your iPhone, home computers and even web servers anywhere. Great value for the price!</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $0.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://bjango.com/apps/">Bjango</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=303034517&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=306785502&amp;mt=8">Ego</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/Ego.jpg" alt="Ego" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>Ego gives you a quick overview of your web statistics from services like Google Analytics but can also check stats on services like Twitter, Vimeo, Squarespace, Mint, Feedburner and Ember. The app is clean and simple to provide a quick view of your current stats. Tapping a service rotates through additional stats.</p>
<p>This is a great app for developers who want to keep track of web stats as well as developing social media stats.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $1.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://garrettmurray.net">Garrett Murray</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=306785502&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<p><!-- SET POINT --></p>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=303689911&amp;mt=8">Analytics App</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/AnalyticsApp.jpg" alt="Analytics App" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>If you&#8217;re looking for a fully featured Google Analytics app, this would be it. You&#8217;ll get quick access to your Google Analytics account, including maps, and all the information you&#8217;ll need. Google changed their API for Analytics so the app is being rewritten and the free update is due out this month.</p>
<p>You&#8217;ll also be able to access all your Google Analytics information via WiFi, 3G or EDGE.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $5.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://analyticsapp.com">AnalyticsApp.com</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=303689911&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=308257679&amp;mt=8">Mint Stats</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/MintStats.jpg" alt="Mint Stats" width="200" height="288" />
</div>
<p>Mint Stats plugs into Shaun Inman&#8217;s <a href="http://haveamint.com">Mint analytics</a> and provides stats for the last 24 hours. Check hourly and daily totals for views and unique visits, manage multiple sites, auto-refresh and more.</p>
<p>Overall, it&#8217;s a pretty basic app but gives you the info. you need while you&#8217;re on the go.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: Free</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://wallerdev.com">Edward Waller</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=308257679&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=303164771&amp;mt=8">Web Developer Bible</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/WebDevelopersBible.jpg" alt="Web Developer Bible" width="200" height="288" />
</div>
<p>The Web Developer Bible app is a very handy reference for RGB to HEX color conversion, HTML entities and more. It&#8217;s a pretty simple app but it could certainly be useful for some web developers and because it&#8217;s free, it&#8217;s definitely worth at least checking out.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: Free</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewArtist?id=301308659">Niranjan Kumar</a> (iTunes Link)</li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=303164771&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=288827448&amp;mt=8">Developer&#8217;s Tool Kit</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/DevelopersToolKit.jpg" alt="Developer&#39;s Tool Kit" width="200" />
</div>
<p>Developer&#8217;s Took Kit combines several helpful tools for developers and designers such as a computer science hex calculator (works with binary, octal and logic operations), color wheel and categorized ANSI UTF-8 character set. The character can be browsed by name, unicode value and symbol type.</p>
<p>The price seems a little much for what&#8217;s included but the calculator is quite helpful and finding UTF-8 characters is a breeze.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $4.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.swamiware.com">Swamiware LLC</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=288827448&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=301093674&amp;mt=8">CSS Cheat Sheet</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/CSSCheatSheet.jpg" alt="CSS Cheat Sheet" width="200" height="288" />
</div>
<p>Learning CSS? Need a refresher course or just a reference sheet for CSS? This is a great app for just that. CSS Cheat Sheet is searchable and easy to browse by category. It includes descriptions, values and examples for backgrounds, borders, classifications, fonts, margins and a whole lot more.</p>
<p>This is probably one of the most thorough CSS reference apps available for the iPhone.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $0.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.concentricsky.com/products/iphone/">Concentric Sky</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=301093674&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=302090867&amp;mt=8">jQuery Cheat Sheet</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/jQueryCheatSheet.jpg" alt="jQuery Cheat Sheet" width="200" height="288" />
</div>
<p>jQuery Cheat Sheet is another reference app from Concentric Sky. If you just need to reference something real quick or even if you&#8217;re new to jQuery, this is a great app to have handy. You can even write and test your jQuery within the app now.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s also important to note that this app doesn&#8217;t retrieve any of its information from the internet, so you can use it anytime, anywhere.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $0.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.concentricsky.com/products/iphone/">Concentric Sky</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=302090867&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=302719350&amp;mt=8">JavaScript Cheat Sheet</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/JavaScriptCheatSheet.jpg" alt="JavaScript Cheat Sheet" width="200" />
</div>
<p>JavaScript Cheat Sheet is another reference app from Concentric Sky. It&#8217;s another great app for learning JavaScript or if you would like a handy reference app for those times you just can&#8217;t remember an expression or something else.</p>
<p>As with Concentric Sky&#8217;s other apps, this one also works completely offline.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $0.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.concentricsky.com/products/iphone/">Concentric Sky</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=302719350&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=303696538&amp;mt=8">HTML Cheat Sheet</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/HTMLCheatSheet.jpg" alt="HTML Cheat Sheet" width="200" height="288" />
</div>
<p>This is probably one of the more popular reference apps from Concentric Sky that also allows you to write and test HTML within the app. Reference everything from tag lists to character sets and more with this.</p>
<p>As with Concentric Sky&#8217;s other reference apps, this is another goodie for beginners and those who would like a quick reference guide in their pocket.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $0.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.concentricsky.com/products/iphone/">Concentric Sky</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=303696538&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=302760278&amp;mt=8">PHP Cheat Sheet</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/PHPCheatSheet.jpg" alt="PHP Cheat Sheet" width="200" height="288" />
</div>
<p>If you&#8217;re a developer, your cheat sheet collection wouldn&#8217;t be complete without Concentric Sky&#8217;s PHP cheat sheet. Again, it&#8217;s great for those who would like a quick reference and for those who might be learning PHP.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $0.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.concentricsky.com/products/iphone/">Concentric Sky</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=302760278&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=285073074&amp;mt=8">WordPress</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/WordPress.jpg" alt="WordPress" width="200" height="288" />
</div>
<p>The WordPress app gives you the power of WordPress in your pocket. Create and edit content on your sites, even if you&#8217;re offline. The app supports true previews, tags, categories, iPhone photo integration and most other functions you can do in WordPress from your desktop.</p>
<p>The app also lets you manage multiple sites if you need.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: Free</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://automattic.com">Automattic, Inc.</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=285073074&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=291211374&amp;mt=8">Blog with iBlogger!</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/iBlogger.jpg" alt="iBlogger" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>iBlogger is a multi-platform capable blogging app for everything from WordPress and TypePad to SquareSpace, Xanga and ExpressionEngine. You can easily manage just about any major blog installation with support for most major features like pictures, tags, links, etc.</p>
<p>If you run multiple blogs on multiple platforms, this is the app you&#8217;ll want for easy mobile access.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $9.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://illuminex.com">illumineX, Inc.</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=291211374&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=285897618&amp;mt=8">1Password</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/1Password.jpg" alt="1Password" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>If you&#8217;re not using a password manager already, you might consider looking for one. 1Password is a popular choice and with iPhone integration, the choice is even easier. Store your information and passwords securely and let it automatically log you into websites with ease.</p>
<p>There&#8217;s a lot you can do with it, especially for the price.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $4.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://agilewebsolutions.com">Agile Web Solutions</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=285897618&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=286411342&amp;mt=8">PassGen</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/PassGen.jpg" alt="PassGen" width="200" height="288" />
</div>
<p>PassGen is a straight forward and basic app that generates random passwords between 4 and 16 digits that will be much more secure than the basic passwords most people use. Once you generate a password, email it to yourself for safe keeping.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: Free</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewArtist?id=286411345">SCB</a> (iTunes Link)</li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=286411342&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=327630330&amp;mt=8">Dropbox</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/Dropbox.jpg" alt="Dropbox" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>As a designer and/or developer, you probably share and sync files with lots of people across many computers. The Dropbox app gives you easy access to your Dropbox.com account files for viewing, managing and sharing while you&#8217;re on the go.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: Free</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.getdropbox.com/iphoneapp">Dropbox</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=327630330&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=288491637&amp;mt=8">SugarSync</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/SugarSync.jpg" alt="SugarSync" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>SugarSync is a service similar to Dropbox and provides easy file access anywhere. The same applies to the iPhone app which lets you view, manage and share your synced files anywhere, anytime. You can even stream entire music collections stored on your computer!</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: Free</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.sugarsync.com/products/mobile_access/sync_iphone.html">Sharpcast, Inc.</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=288491637&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=292416855&amp;mt=8">Discover</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/Discover.jpg" alt="Discover" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>Discover lets you use your iPhone as a wireless mobile hard drive via WiFi. You (or others) can connect and transfer or share files. It even works iPhone to iPhone. Within the app you can also view all the major document formats including Microsoft Office, PDF&#8217;s, HTML and other text based files and many more.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: Free</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.mappn.com">mAPPn, Inc.</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=292416855&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=289943355&amp;mt=8">Air Sharing (Document Viewer, File Storage)</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/AirSharing.jpg" alt="Air Sharing" width="200" height="288" />
</div>
<p>Air Sharing gives you drag and drop access to your iPhone over WiFi when mounted as a wireless drive on Mac, Windows or Linux. You can also connect through a browser if necessary. You can view literally just about every major file format available including Microsoft Office and iWork files.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $4.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://avatron.com/apps/">Avatron Software, Inc.</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=289943355&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=285578660&amp;mt=8">Files</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/Files.jpg" alt="Files" width="200" height="288" />
</div>
<p>Store and view files on your iPhone with the Files app, again, over WiFi. You can also email and password protect your files if needed. Files also supports all major file formats such as Microsoft Office and Apple iWork. Once you&#8217;ve viewed files, the app can even remember the page and zoom level.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $4.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.olivetoast.com/Files/">Olive Toast</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=285578660&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=304673686&amp;mt=8">Quickoffice Files</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/QuickofficeFiles.jpg" alt="Quickoffice Files" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>Quickoffice Files is part of an online service for managing your office files but the app can be used independently as well. Transfer files via WiFi, view, email and password protect files and even access your MobileMe iDisk account.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $0.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.quickoffice.com/?product_info=quickoffice_files_iphone&amp;os_listing=iPhone_OS">Quickoffice, Inc.</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=304673686&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=283292597&amp;mt=8">Sketches</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/Sketches.jpg" alt="Sketches" width="200" height="288" />
</div>
<p>Sketches lets you easily jot down notes and thoughts as well as annotate your pictures and more. It&#8217;s sort of a cross between a fun and creative drawing and annotation app and something that also serves its purposes for business. You can also send your creations once you&#8217;re done.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $4.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.latenitesoft.com">LateNiteSoft</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=283292597&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=291664204&amp;mt=8">iBlueSky (mindmapping)</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/iBlueSky.jpg" alt="iBlueSky" width="200" height="288" />
</div>
<p>As designers and developers, we get ideas all the timeregardless of location. iBlueSky lets you ditch the paper napkin and take brainstorming and problem solving to a new level. When you&#8217;re done you can send via email in Novamind, PDF, PNG, OPML and more formats.</p>
<p>There&#8217;s many more great functions with this app as well as integration with Box.net. The price seems a bit steep but it&#8217;s hard to put a price on great ideas right?</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $9.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewArtist?id=291664207">Tenero Software Limited</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=291664204&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=284971781&amp;mt=8">Things</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/Things.jpg" alt="Things" width="200" height="288" />
</div>
<p>Things for the iPhone brings the power of Things for the desktop, to your iPhone. Wirelessly sync your lists and tasks when you&#8217;re near your computer. The great thing about this app though, is you don&#8217;t need the desktop application. Things for the iPhone is an independent app, thus the rather steep price.</p>
<p>Things simplifies task management and makes it much easier to stay productive and keep track of life anywhere you might be.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $9.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://culturedcode.com/things/iphone/">Cultured Code</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=284971781&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=293561396&amp;mt=8">Remember The Milk</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/RememberTheMilk.jpg" alt="Remember The Milk" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>Remember The Milk (RTM) connects with the online service to sync your lists and tasks. You can also work offline and sync when the internet is available. RTM is a super simple and easy to use app and service but also provides the options and flexibility you might need.</p>
<p>RTM also has lots of integration with the iPhone such as detecting location for nearby tasks and much more.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: Free</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.rememberthemilk.com/services/iphone/app/">Remember The Milk</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=293561396&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=320666764&amp;mt=8">MiniBooks for FreshBooks</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/Freshbooks.jpg" alt="MiniBooks for FreshBooks" width="200" height="288" />
</div>
<p>MiniBooks brings the popular invoicing software, FreshBooks, to the iPhone. As far as I can tell, it&#8217;s an independent application that is capable of syncing with your online FreshBooks account (if not, the price is way steep). You get all the features and power of FreshBooks while you&#8217;re on the go.</p>
<p>There&#8217;s also a lite version available which I believe requires a FreshBooks account.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $14.99 &#8211; Lite: Free</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.freshbooks.com/minibooks/">Groovy Squared</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=320666764&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a> &#8211; <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=322591584&amp;mt=8">Download Lite from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=293731095&amp;mt=8">Jobs &#8211; Time Sheet + Tracking</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/Jobs.jpg" alt="Jobs" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>Jobs is a simple time tracking and time sheet creation app. It&#8217;s important to keep track of your time to make sure you get paid. Jobs features multiple timers, sessions, exporting, different currencies and more.</p>
<p>The nice thing about Jobs is that it&#8217;s not bloated with extra crap you don&#8217;t need. That way it&#8217;s easy as pie to keep track of your time.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $1.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://bjango.com/apps/jobs/">Bjango</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=293731095&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=283646709&amp;mt=8">PayPal</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/PayPal.jpg" alt="PayPal" width="200" height="300" />
</div>
<p>Most of you are familiar with PayPal. If you&#8217;re not yet, you most likely will be soon. PayPal for the iPhone gives you quick access to your account for checking your balance, reviewing history, sending money and more. In fact, it&#8217;s so fast and easy, I use it to check my account even while I&#8217;m at the computer.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: Free</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.paypal.com">PayPal</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=283646709&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=291720439&amp;mt=8">BeejiveIM 3.0 with Push</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/Beejive.jpg" alt="BeejiveIM" width="200" height="288" />
</div>
<p>Beejive is arguably the best iPhone instant messaging app around that&#8217;s more capable than some desktop messaging clients. Connect to all the major services such as AIM, Windows Live, Yahoo!, GoogleTalk, Facebook, Myspace&#8230; and the list goes on. It also moves from 3G/EDGE to WiFi seamlessly and is capable of push notifications after you close the app.</p>
<p>I communicate with many clients via chat and this makes it easy to take my chats with me anywhere.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $9.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://www.beejive.com">Beejive, Inc.</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=291720439&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=320876271&amp;mt=8">Prowl: Growl Client</a></h3>
<div class="postimage">
	<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/506_iphone/images/Prowl.jpg" alt="Prowl: Growl Client" width="200" height="288" />
</div>
<p>Prowl is simply a Growl client for the iPhone. Get push notifications from your Mac or Windows computer for anything you configure Growl with and would like push notifications on your iPhone. It&#8217;s all highly configurable to fit your needs.</p>
<p>I personally use it for multiple email accounts, messaging, system alerts and a lot more.</p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $2.99</li>
<li>Developer: <a href="http://prowl.weks.net">Zachary West</a></li>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=320876271&amp;mt=8">Download from iTunes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="clear"></div>
<h3>Conclusion</h3>
<p>Well, there you have it fellow web designers and developers. 50 fantastic iPhone apps for taking on many of our daily tasks anytime, anywhere, from the convenience of a pocket sized device. As I mentioned at the beginning, there are several other options for many of these app types. I couldn&#8217;t include them all though or this list would be a mile long. These are the ones I&#8217;ve picked from personal experience and reviews during my own searches for apps to make my job a little easier.</p>
<p>As I&#8217;m sure we all are, I&#8217;m always on the lookout for fresh new apps to make my web design or development tasks easier, faster or more mobile. So, if you know of any really great apps, please share them with us in the comments below. Thanks!</p>
<p><em>Thanks so much to <a href="http://www.suberapps.com">SuberApps</a> for the use of the post image! </em></p>
<ul class="webroundup">
<li>Follow us on <a href="http://www.twitter.com/nettuts">Twitter</a>, or subscribe to the <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/nettuts" title="Nettuts+ RSS Feed">Nettuts+ RSS Feed</a> for the best web development tutorials on the web.</li>
</ul>
<p>
<script type="text/javascript"><!--digg_url = "post permalink (not digg url)"; // -->
</script><br />
<script src="http://digg.com/tools/diggthis.js" type="text/javascript"></script></p>

<p><a href="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/5VsfmBNqEW37b73h2VmkcicLQvs/0/da"><img src="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/5VsfmBNqEW37b73h2VmkcicLQvs/0/di" border="0" ismap="true"></img></a><br/>
<a href="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/5VsfmBNqEW37b73h2VmkcicLQvs/1/da"><img src="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/5VsfmBNqEW37b73h2VmkcicLQvs/1/di" border="0" ismap="true"></img></a></p><div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=OzHUFqmZn8U:G4zsiaD6-PI:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=OzHUFqmZn8U:G4zsiaD6-PI:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=OzHUFqmZn8U:G4zsiaD6-PI:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=OzHUFqmZn8U:G4zsiaD6-PI:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=OzHUFqmZn8U:G4zsiaD6-PI:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=OzHUFqmZn8U:G4zsiaD6-PI:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=OzHUFqmZn8U:G4zsiaD6-PI:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=OzHUFqmZn8U:G4zsiaD6-PI:TzevzKxY174"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?d=TzevzKxY174" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/nettuts/~4/OzHUFqmZn8U" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://net.tutsplus.com/articles/web-roundups/50-helpful-iphone-apps-for-web-designers-and-developers/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>62</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://net.tutsplus.com/articles/web-roundups/50-helpful-iphone-apps-for-web-designers-and-developers/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>ASP.NET from Scratch: Lesson 2</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/nettuts/~3/VSdErXJEmR0/</link>
		<comments>http://net.tutsplus.com/videos/screencasts/asp-net-from-scratch-lesson-2/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2009 10:30:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jeremy McPeak</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Screencasts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asp.net]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://net.tutsplus.com/?p=7987</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<img src="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/481_asp/aspnetFromScratch.jpg" alt="ASP.NET from Scratch : Lesson 2" />]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
Continuing on from <a href="http://net.tutsplus.com/videos/screencasts/asp-net-from-scratch-lesson-1/">lesson one</a>, Jeremy McPeak, author of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0470109491/">Professional AJAX</a>, and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0470525932/">Beginning JavaScript: 4th Edition</a>, will take things a step further as we delve deeper into working with the ASP.NET framework.
</p>
<p><span id="more-7987"></span></p>
<div class="tutorial_image">
<a href="http://nettuts.s3.amazonaws.com/507_asp/AspDotNetFromScratch_Part2.zip"><img src="http://nettuts.com/wp-content/themes/nettuts/site_images/button_src_nm.jpg"></a>
</div>
<h3>The Complete Series </h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://net.tutsplus.com/videos/screencasts/asp-net-from-scratch-lesson-1/">Lesson 1</a></li>
<li><a href="#">Lesson 2</a></li>
</ul>
<h3>Screencast</h3>
<div class="tutorial_image">
<embed src="http://blip.tv/play/gcMVgbLjYAA%2Em4v" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" width="600" height="453" allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true"></embed>
</div>
<h3>Other Viewing Options</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewPodcast?i=60856588&#038;id=291173544">iTunes/Download Version</a></li>
</ul>
<ul class="webroundup">
<li>Follow us on <a href="http://www.twitter.com/nettuts">Twitter</a>, or subscribe to the <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/nettuts" title="Nettuts+ RSS Feed">Nettuts+ RSS Feed</a> for the best web development tutorials on the web.</li>
</ul>
<p>
<script type="text/javascript"><!--digg_url = "post permalink (not digg url)"; // -->
</script><br />
<script src="http://digg.com/tools/diggthis.js" type="text/javascript"></script></p>

<p><a href="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/Pk8HaSgFzSnyGmcVuzGYZZiXvEc/0/da"><img src="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/Pk8HaSgFzSnyGmcVuzGYZZiXvEc/0/di" border="0" ismap="true"></img></a><br/>
<a href="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/Pk8HaSgFzSnyGmcVuzGYZZiXvEc/1/da"><img src="http://feedads.g.doubleclick.net/~a/Pk8HaSgFzSnyGmcVuzGYZZiXvEc/1/di" border="0" ismap="true"></img></a></p><div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=VSdErXJEmR0:dBfV0QhAX5A:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=VSdErXJEmR0:dBfV0QhAX5A:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=VSdErXJEmR0:dBfV0QhAX5A:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=VSdErXJEmR0:dBfV0QhAX5A:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=VSdErXJEmR0:dBfV0QhAX5A:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=VSdErXJEmR0:dBfV0QhAX5A:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?i=VSdErXJEmR0:dBfV0QhAX5A:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?a=VSdErXJEmR0:dBfV0QhAX5A:TzevzKxY174"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/nettuts?d=TzevzKxY174" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/nettuts/~4/VSdErXJEmR0" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://net.tutsplus.com/videos/screencasts/asp-net-from-scratch-lesson-2/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>37</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://net.tutsplus.com/videos/screencasts/asp-net-from-scratch-lesson-2/</feedburner:origLink></item>
	</channel>
</rss><!--
This site's performance optimized by W3 Total Cache:

W3 Total Cache improves the user experience of your blog by caching
frequent operations, reducing the weight of various files and providing
transparent content delivery network integration.

Learn more about our WordPress Plugins: http://www.w3-edge.com/wordpress-plugins/

Page Caching using memcached
Database Caching 22/27 queries in 1.280 seconds using memcached
Content Delivery Network via 

Served from: psdtutsplus.com @ 2009-12-07 13:22:12 -->
